<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Herod and Pilate reconciled: or The concord of papist and puritan (against Scripture, fathers, councels, and other orthodoxall writers) for the coercion, deposition, and killing of kings. Discouered by David Owen Batchelour of Diuinitie, and chaplaine to the right Honourable Lord Vicount Hadington</title>
            <author>Owen, David, d. 1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18983.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113808</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849038</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849038</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14168</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68537)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14168)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1180:6, 1837:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Herod and Pilate reconciled: or The concord of papist and puritan (against Scripture, fathers, councels, and other orthodoxall writers) for the coercion, deposition, and killing of kings. Discouered by David Owen Batchelour of Diuinitie, and chaplaine to the right Honourable Lord Vicount Hadington</title>
                  <author>Owen, David, d. 1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 75 [i.e. 57], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Cantrell Legge, printer to the Vniversitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P. 57 misnumbered 75.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18983 on UMI microfilm reel 1180.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Bodleian Library and the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1180 (Bodleian Library copy) and at reel 1837 (Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14168:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod and Pilate reconciled:</hi> OR, THE CONCORD OF PAPIST AND PVRITAN (A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scripture, Fathers, Councels, and other <hi>Orthodoxall Writers) for the Coercion,</hi> Depoſition, and Killing <hi>of</hi> KINGS.</p>
            <p>Diſcouered by <hi>David Owen</hi> Batchelour of Diuinitie, <hi>and Chaplaine to the right Honourable Lord Vicount</hi> HADINGTON.</p>
            <q>Tunc inter ſe concordant, cum in perniciem iuſti conſpirant, non quia ſe amant, ſed quia eum qui amandus erat ſimul ode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal. 36. concion. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>PRINTED BY <hi>CANTRELL LEGGE,</hi> Printer to the Vniverſitie of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14168:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14168:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, <hi>SIR IOHN RAMSEY</hi> Knight, Lord Vicount <hi>Hadington,</hi> one of the moſt <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Gentlemen of the Kings Maieſties</hi> bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, my ſingular good Lord, <hi>and Maſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Did ſuppoſe <hi>(my very good Lord)</hi> that the ſembable oppoſition of <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Puritane,</hi> againſt the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>ſupremacie Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Kings,</hi> might haue beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriued into a fewe ſheetes of paper; which I finde both tedious, and intricate: becauſe the opponents, (though they agree againſt <hi>Kings,</hi> as <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> did againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi>) are at diuers irreconciliable iarres among themſelues. And no maruell, <hi>quia menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij multiplex diuortium:</hi> Liers neuer agree in one tale. There are among the <hi>Papiſts</hi> three different opinions concerning the <hi>Popes</hi> power ouer <hi>Kings.</hi> The firſt opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which<note n="a" place="margin">Alexand. Car. de poteſt. Rom. Pontif. lib. 2. c. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander Carerius</hi> holdeth) is, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath abſolute power ouer all the world, both in Eccleſiaſticall, and Politicall things. The ſecond opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is <hi>Bellarmines,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Bellar. de Pontif. lib. 5. c. 6.</note> who affirmeth, that though the <hi>Pope</hi> haue not meere temporall power ouer <hi>Kings,</hi> and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, <hi>directly;</hi> yet hath he ſupreame authoritie to diſpoſe of the Temporalities of all Chriſtians, as well
<pb facs="tcp:14168:3"/>
Kings, as others, by <hi>an indirect prerogatiue,</hi> tending to the aduancement of the ſpirituall good. The third is the opinion of<note n="c" place="margin">Guliel Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clay. cont. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchomacos, l. 5. cap. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Barclayus,</hi> who auerreth, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath ſpirituall power to excommunicate Kings, but no tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall authoritie, <hi>directly,</hi> or <hi>indirectly,</hi> to <hi>afflict</hi> the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Kings, to <hi>tranſpoſe</hi> their kingdomes, to perſwade forrainers to make warres, or ſubiects to rebell againſt them. And with him agreeth M. <hi>Blackwell</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">In the letter annexed to his large examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, p. 157.</note> in his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Romiſh Catholiques of England,</hi> wherein he ſaith, that the <hi>keyes Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> doe no way extend themſelues by <hi>Gods</hi> law, vnto kingdomes terrene, to open or ſhut, to toſſe, or turmoile any of them, they haue no wardes in them, to turne, or ouerturne Kingdomes, or to open any lawfull entrance, into ſuch diſobedient and doubtfull courſes. Whereſoeuer <hi>(moſt noble Lord)</hi> any <hi>Papiſt</hi> hath laid a ſtepping-ſtone in this water of ſtrife, any man may plainely trace the <hi>Puritanes treading.</hi> Although they denie an vniuerſall abſolute power ouer all Kings, which the Pope claymeth, they contend for a <hi>nationall ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie,</hi> in euery kingdome, ouer Kings, to diſpoſe of them and their kingdomes. <hi>Although the Popes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſtopher Goodman</hi>)<note n="e" place="margin">Treatiſe of obedience, pag. 52. 53.</note> 
               <hi>for ſundrie enormities, haue depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Kings, by vnlawfull authoritie; the reaſon that mooued them ſo to doe, was honeſt, and iuſt, and meete to be receiued, and executed by the bodie of euery common-wealth.</hi> haec ille. <hi>The Stateſmen of the kingdome</hi> (ſaith<note n="f" place="margin">Polit. Chriſt. l 6. c. 3. p. 156.</note> 
               <hi>Lambertus Danaeus) may puniſh their King when he tranſgreſſeth the fundamentall lawes of the kingdome, yea if he be obſtinate, they may depriue him of his royall dignitie.</hi> M. <hi>Beza</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Theſes Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venſes, p. 249.</note> in a ſcholaſticall diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation (one <hi>Iohn Iobert</hi> beeing Reſpondent) did deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, that <hi>the officers of State, ſuch as are the</hi> 7. <hi>Electors in the Empire of the Romanes, and the Three States in euery Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie,
<pb facs="tcp:14168:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
haue authoritie to repreſſe tyrannous Princes: which if they doe not, they ſhall anſwer before God, for their treacherie</hi> againſt the people. <hi>Dudley Fenner</hi> an Engliſh Sectarie, iumpeth with them: <hi>He is a Tyrant by practiſe</hi> (ſaith<note n="h" place="margin">Sacra Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia. lib. 5 c. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) that diſſolueth all, or the chiefeſt compacts of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, let them that haue that authoritie, as the Peeres of the kingdome, or the publike aſſemblie of all Eſtates, make him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> vel pacificè, vel cum bello, <hi>either by peaceable practiſe, or open hoſtilitie.</hi> Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> giueth this reaſon for the Popes indirect power ouer Kings:<note n="*" place="margin">De Pontif l. 5. cap. 7.</note> 
               <hi>The Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Commonwealth muſt be</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>perfect, and of it ſelfe ſufficient, to attaine vnto the ende whereunto it was ordained: for ſuch are all Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>wealths that are well inſtituted. Therfore it ought to haue all neceſſarie power, to attaine to the ſpirituall end, but power to diſpoſe of all temporalties, is neceſſarie to the ſpirituall end: for otherwiſe euill Kings will foſter heretikes, and ouerthrow religion, wherfore the Church hath this power.</hi> Haec ille. <hi>Banoſus</hi> a <hi>Puritane</hi> in a tractate of Ciuill and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Politie, hath the very ſame reaſon, for the power of the <hi>Preſbiterie:</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">lib. 2. pag 51.</note> 
               <hi>If the Church</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>haue not power, by forcible meanes to compell all ſorts of men to liue in order, this abſurditie will follow, euen vnder a faithfull magiſtrate, that the Church can not defend her ſelfe, with her owne forces. What (I pray you) will become of the Church, when the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is either an Infidel, or ſo negligent, as to ſuffer euill to be done without puniſhment? and thoſe things which are hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be profaned, or remooued? Should not the Church be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ouerthrowne in theſe eaſes, if it had not peculiar right to make powerfull reſiſtance? Haec ille.</hi> I appeale <hi>(my good Lord)</hi> to the conſciences of all good men, whether this reaſon of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Banoſus</hi> be not a wicked ouerthwarting
<pb facs="tcp:14168:4"/>
of the counſell of God, and his gratious prouidence, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Church, yea an open bewraying of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet hearts, and ſeditious diſpoſition. Our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> (foreſeeing and foreſhewing, that his <hi>Diſciples</hi> the chiefe pillars of the Church, ſhould be brought before <hi>Kings, hated of the world,</hi> yea and put to <hi>death</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Matth 10.18 &amp;c 24 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for his <hi>names ſake,</hi>) teacheth not, to reſiſt, or rebell, but to abide, and<note n="l" place="margin">Matth. 24.13.</note> endure, not with violence to withſtand authoritie, but<note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 21.19.</note> with <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to poſseſſe their ſoules.</hi> This is a remedie againſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and there is no other meanes reuealed in the word of God againſt perſecution then<note n="n" place="margin">Matth. 10.23.</note> 
               <hi>Deſertion: if they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you in one citie, flie to an other:</hi> or<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.15.</note> Praier and Patience; <hi>Happie</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>are you, when men ſhall doe all manner of euill vnto you for my names ſake, reioyce and be glad, for great is your reward in heauen.</hi> Let not man therfore reſiſt their power, which <hi>God</hi> ordained, but with all meeknes endure perſecution in earth, that they may be crowned in heauen. <hi>Lambertus Danaeus</hi> a <hi>Puritane</hi> of the beſt note, doth freely graunt <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines Theſis, viz.</hi> that there is a power <hi>in ordine ad ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualia,</hi> to puniſh kings: denying his <hi>hypotheſis, viz.</hi> that the Pope hath ſuch power. <hi>This beeing granted</hi> (ſaith<note n="q" place="margin">Reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Dan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ella<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de pontif. lib. 5. cap. 7. pag. 541.</note> 
               <hi>Danaeus) that Bellarmine contendeth for: it doth not followe that the Biſhop of Rome, or any other Prelate, hath temporall iuriſdiction ouer that ciuill Chriſtian Magiſtrate, which doth either enact lawes againſt the ſpirituall determination: or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the Commonwealth contrarie to the ſpirituall regiment of the Church. We confeſſe thoſe lawes, and that gouernement, ſhould be reformed, but it ought to be done, by the publike aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, by the Parliament of the kingdome, or by the Peeres themſelues of the whole kingdome.</hi> Yea in caſe the king de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be depoſed, <hi>the Pope, and other Biſhops, or Prieſts,
<pb facs="tcp:14168:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
haue no right to dethrone him:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Neither batell better hering.</note> 
               <hi>Verùm id fieri debet</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Idem ibidem pag. 517.</note> 
               <hi>à con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio publico, à Parliamento regni, vel ab ipſis regni ordinibus,</hi> but that ought to be done by the publike Councell, the Parliament of the kingdome, or by the Eſtates of the land: <hi>Haec ille.</hi> Thus farre <hi>(my good Lord)</hi> they agree in ſubſtance, touching the <hi>puniſhment,</hi> and <hi>depriuation</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> though they vary in this point of circumſtance, whether the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Peeres,</hi> or the <hi>people</hi> ſhall puniſh or depoſe them.</p>
            <p>As concerning the third opinion, which is for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication of Kings; all <hi>Preſbyteries</hi> which are the tribunall ſeates of Ieſus Chriſt (as <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith in his book againſt <hi>Eraſtus</hi>) do chalenge right and power,<note place="margin">Theodorus Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za, pag. 116. Guli l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Diſcipl. Eccl ſi.</note> as Chriſts immediate Commiſſaries in earth, to excommunicate the chiefe Chriſtian Magiſtrates, as may appeare by theſe places: <hi>viz. Beza de Preſbyterio, pag.</hi> 115.<note place="margin">Thomas Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright. Lamb. Danaeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Gellius Sneca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> in his laſt reply, <hi>pag.</hi> 65. <hi>Lambertus Danaeus</hi> in his Chriſtian Policy, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 232. <hi>Gellius Snecanus</hi> in his booke of diſcipline, <hi>pag.</hi> 456.<note place="margin">Gali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Herm Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>William Bucanus</hi> in his common places of Diuinitie, <hi>pag.</hi> 582. <hi>Hermanus Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherus</hi> in his obſeruation vpon the firſt Pſalme, <hi>pag:</hi> 68.<note place="margin">The counter p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſon. The humble petition. The defence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The counterpoyſon, <hi>pag.</hi> 175. The humble petition to the late Queene, <hi>pag.</hi> 55. And the defence of diſcipline againſt <hi>M. Bridges, pag.</hi> 127. And this power, haue they put in practiſe <hi>to the glorie of Sion,</hi> againſt diuerſe kings in the Chriſtian world, as the ſaid <hi>diſciplinarian</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>8</note> 
               <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion</hi> boaſteth, in more then inſolent manner. Conſider <hi>(honourable Lord)</hi> whether any King may thinke his ſtate ſecure, where euery <hi>offence,</hi> though but ſuſpected, doth procure a <hi>citation,</hi> euerie <hi>citation,</hi> doth inforce <hi>apparence,</hi> euery <hi>apparence</hi> doth vrge <hi>confeſsion,</hi> or inioyne <hi>purgation,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14168:5"/>
and the leaſt <hi>contempt</hi> doth breed a <hi>contumacie,</hi> to drawe the <hi>greateſt cenſure.</hi> Theſe <hi>Pariſh-popes</hi> ſhall neuer be able to ſhewe any record in the ſanctuarie, or practiſe of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, for a thouſand yeares after Chriſt to warrant this <hi>Puritan-popiſh</hi> manner of proceeding againſt Princes. I like well of the opinion in <hi>Iohn de Pariſijs</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">De poteſt. reg. &amp; papal. cap. 13. Euerie Miniſter of God muſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubmit his life to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces pleaſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admit him to the Sacrament, that ſheweth manifeſt tokens of impietie, or infidelitie: but the Puritans ſpeake not of the Church mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, but of their Lordly conſiſtorie, at the Papiſts due of the Popes court: whom not God but the Deuill and Antich iſt hath exalted ouer Kings.</note> concerning the power of the Keyes. <hi>Non quilibet peccator, &amp;c. Euery offender, neither is nor ought to be ſubiect to the power of the keyes, and Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction, but the ſinner which is ſubiect thereto. And therefore the ſaid power hath no effect, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt them that are ſubiect vnto it, which ſubiection, maketh a man fit matter, whereupon the power of the keyes hath his effectuall operation. Haec ille.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The politique Puritans meddle not with this dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous queſtion, of Depoſing and Killing of Kings, but ſtand aloofe, to giue ayme, while other deſperat, archers ſhoote, that if they miſſe, they may ſtep aſide to ſaue themſelues, or in caſe the marke be hit, they may ſtep in to part the ſtakes. I accuſe not without cauſe: M. <hi>Beza</hi> beeing ſeriouſly conſulted by ſome brethern of England, whether inferiour officers, might not lawfully arme themſelues, againſt him, who beeing lawfully confirmed Magiſtrate, doth take away the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges, and infringe the liberties, which he hath ſworne to performe to the ſubiects; or doth oppreſſe them with manifeſt tyrannie, &amp;c. returned this fectleſſe anſwer,<note n="u" place="margin">Beza epiſt. 24.</note> 
               <hi>cogitmur</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>We muſt demurre vpon this point, not onely becauſe it is dangerous (ſpecially in our time) to ſet open ſuch a window, but alſo for that we may not determine the ſtate of this queſtion, ſimply as you propound it, but vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of many moſt waightie circumſtances.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Ira<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in hoc Aphroriſmo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:14168:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for the preſent we deferre our anſwer to your demaund:</hi> Thus <hi>Beza</hi> demurred at <hi>Geneua, in communi fratrum ex verbe, &amp; agro collectorum caetu,</hi> in the common aſſembly of the Brethren, out of the Citie, and Suburbes: 25. <hi>Iunij. Anno Domini.</hi> 1568. the very yeare before <hi>Morton the Popes Nuncio,</hi> came to <hi>England,</hi> to ſtirre vp the Peeres of the North, againſt our late <hi>Queene,</hi> for pretended <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> and <hi>tyrannie.</hi> While the propoſition was demurred at <hi>Geneva,</hi> the Aſſumption was framed at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the concluſion practiſed by traytors in <hi>England;</hi> could not <hi>Beza</hi> anſwer? why did he not confeſſe it? or if he could, why doth he diſſemble it? It is truth without colour that muſt direct the conſcience, and ſettle the ſimple, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be reſolued. <hi>Diſſimulation</hi> is but dawbing with vntempered morter, <hi>ad perdendos homines in ſermone men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacij,</hi> to bring men to deſtruction, with the words of lying: and a verie readie way to bring <hi>religion</hi> to ſcandale <hi>Princes</hi> to iealouſie, and <hi>male-contented</hi> men to mutinie. I haue endeuoured (according to my mediocritie of learning) to ſet downe the iudgement of the Church of God in all the former ages, concerning the <hi>Authoritie of Kings,</hi> and the <hi>Dutie of ſubiects,</hi> that the late learning of <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Puritane,</hi> (compared with the old doctrine of ancient Orthodoxals) may appeare to be as new as it is naught: which I offer to your Honourable protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, aſwell in reſpect of your <hi>dutie to God,</hi> as of <hi>my ſeruice to your Lordſhip.</hi> Your <hi>dutie to God:</hi> for he that hath made you his <hi>inſtrument of honour</hi> to ſaue the <hi>Kings life,</hi> doth require at your hands, the maintenance of the <hi>Kings right.</hi> And ſeeing it hath pleaſed you, to admit <hi>me into the number of your ſervants,</hi> I hope you will fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb facs="tcp:14168:6"/>
accept of this my <hi>ſeruice,</hi> wherein I doe my beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour, to make vp the gappe againſt <hi>Schiſme</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>ſedition</hi> in the <hi>State.</hi> The great <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>King of heauen</hi> graunt your Lordſhip many dayes, much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the loue of your Countrie, inward peace, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting glorie. <hi>From Clarehall in Cambridge.</hi> 12. Octo. 1610.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Chaplaine humbly devoted, <hi>DAVID OVVEN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14168:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the dutifull Subiect.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Puritan-Church-Policie,</hi> and the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiticall ſocietie</hi> began together:<note n="a" place="margin">See M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers preface. And the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. before his examen againſt the firſt part of the Councell of Trent.</note> the one in <hi>Geneva,</hi> 1536. and the other in <hi>Rome,</hi> 1537. ſince their beginning, they haue beſtirred themſelues buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>(as he that compaſſeth the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iob. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>earth, or they that coaſted</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 23.15.</note> 
               <hi>ſea &amp; land,)</hi> each one in his order. The <hi>Puritan</hi> to breake downe the wall of <hi>Sion,</hi> by diſturbing the peace of the <hi>reformed Church:</hi> the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> to build vp the ruines of <hi>Babylon,</hi> by maintaining the abhomination of the <hi>deformed Synagogue.</hi> Theſe (though brethren in ſedition and headie) are <hi>head-ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> the one ſtaring to the <hi>preſbyterie,</hi> and the other to the <hi>Papacie,</hi> but they are ſo faſt linked behind, and <hi>tayle-tied</hi> together with <hi>firebrands</hi> betweene them, that if they be not quenched by the power of Maieſtie, they cannot choſe (when the meanes are fitted to their plot) but ſet the <hi>Church</hi> on fire, and the <hi>ſtate</hi> in an vprore. Their <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and long prayers,</hi> their <hi>much vehement preaching,</hi> and ſtout oppoſition againſt <hi>orders eſtabliſhed,</hi> their ſhewe of auſteritie in their conuerſation, and of ſingular learning in their profeſſion, <hi>(as the euill fiend transformed into an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of light)</hi> brought them firſt to admiration. Whereby they haue not onely <hi>robbed widows houſes</hi> vnder pretence of prayer, and ranſacked their <hi>ſeduced diſciples</hi> by ſhew of
<pb facs="tcp:14168:7"/>
deevotion, but alſo battered the <hi>courts of Princes,</hi> by ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating the <hi>Peeres</hi> againſt <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>people</hi> againſt the <hi>Peeres</hi> for pretended <hi>reformation.</hi> And whereas God hath inſeparably annexed to the <hi>crowne of earthly maieſtie, a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme eccleſiasticall ſoueraigntie</hi> for the protection of <hi>pietie;</hi> and an abſolute <hi>immunitie</hi> from the iudiciall <hi>ſentence,</hi> and Martiall <hi>violence,</hi> for the preſeruation of <hi>policie:</hi> Theſe ſectaries bereaue Kings of both theſe their <hi>Princely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.3.4.</note> exalting themſelues</hi> (as the ſonne of perdition) <hi>aboue all that is called God:</hi> Leaſt they might ſeeme <hi>ſine ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione inſanire,</hi> to ſowe the ſeedes of ſedition without ſhewe of reaſon, <hi>Caedem faciunt ſcripturarum</hi> (as the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time were wont to doe) <hi>in materiam ſuam,</hi> they kill the Scripture to ſerve their turnes: and pervert the holy word of the <hi>eternall God,</hi> by ſtrange in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and wicked application againſt the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> by whom it was penned; the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Church,</hi> to whom it was deliuered; and the practiſe of all the <hi>Godly,</hi> (as well vnder the <hi>Lawe</hi> as the <hi>Goſpel</hi>) that did beleeue, vnderſtand, and obey it; to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their late, and lewd opinions. I haue in my hand <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue fortie ſeveral places of the old and new Testament,</hi> which both the brethren of the enraged oppoſite faction doe indifferently quote, and ſeditiouſly apply, in defence of their dangerous oppoſition, and damnable error, againſt the <hi>Eccleſiasticall ſupremacie,</hi> and the <hi>indeleble character of royal invnction.</hi> Vnto the which places, falſly expounded, perverted, and applyed, I haue added the interpretation, of the learned <hi>Protestants</hi> ſince the time of <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> who began to diſcouer the nakedneſſe of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church,</hi> 1517. More eſpecially inſiſting in the<note n="a" place="margin">K. Henry 8. K Iames. Th. Cranmer. lo. Whitgift. Rich. Bancroft Archb. of Cant. Henry Earle of Northampton. Robert Earle of Salisbury.</note> moſt
<pb facs="tcp:14168:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
mightie Kings, the moſt reuerend Prelats,<note place="margin">The L. Burleigh L. treaſurer of England. The L. Elſ nere L. chancelor of England. The L. Stafford. The L. Cooke. B. Iewell. B. Horn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> B. Pilkington. B Elmere, B Couper. B. Bilſon. B. Babington. B. Andrewes. B. Barlowe. B. Bridges. D Ackworth. D. Sarania. D. Coſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. D. Sutchliffe. D. Prvthet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. D. Wilkes D. Morton. D. Tochen. M. Bekinſaw. M. Foxe. M. Nowell. M. Hooker &amp; many others.</note> honourable Lords, loyall Clergie, and other worthie men, that haue in the Church of England, learnedly defended the Princely right, againſt diſloyall, and vndutifull oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents: which by <hi>Gods</hi> helpe I meane to publiſh, when I haue added the expoſition of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> to confute the falſhood of the <hi>Puritan-popiſh-faction,</hi> &amp; to confirme the truth of the <hi>Proteſtants Doctrine</hi> in each particular quotation. I proteſt in all ſinceritie, that I neither haue in this treatiſe, nor meane in the other, <hi>hereafter to be publiſhed,</hi> to detort any thing, to make either the <hi>cauſe</hi> it ſelfe, or the <hi>fauourers</hi> of it more <hi>odious,</hi> then their owne words, (publiſhed with the generall approbation of their ſeuerall fauorites) doe truely inferre, and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily inforce. I hope the loyall ſubiect, and <hi>Godly</hi> affected, will accept in good part my endeauour, and induſtrie, intended for the glorie of <hi>God,</hi> the honour of the <hi>King,</hi> and the diſcouerie of <hi>the ſeditious.</hi> The diſpleaſure of the <hi>malecontented-factious</hi> (which can no more abide the truth, then the owles can light, or the frantique the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian) I neither regard nor care for. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 10. l. 15. for ſubtilly, read ſubtilty. p. 17. l. 4. <hi>preſto,</hi> for <hi>praeſto.</hi> p. 19. l. 25. <hi>Sabanianus,</hi> for <hi>Sabinianus.</hi> p. 34. l. 27. odience, for obedience. p. 37. l. 13. his, for this. p. 39. l. 5. as very foole, for, as very a foole. p. 47. l. 1. <hi>regnum,</hi> for <hi>regum.</hi> p. 48. l. 17. Prince, for Princes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:14168:8"/>
            <head>The Table of the Booke.</head>
            <p>The
<list>
                  <item>dutie of
<list>
                        <item>Prelates,</item>
                        <item>Peeres,</item>
                        <item>People,</item>
                     </list>
by
<list>
                        <item>Scripture, <hi>Chap. 1. Pag. 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Fathers of the
<list>
                              <item>firſt <hi>300</hi> yeares, <hi>2 pag. 3</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>ſecond <hi>300</hi> yeares, <hi>3 pag. 8</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>third <hi>300</hi> yeares, <hi>cap. 4 pag. 21</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>fourth <hi>300</hi> yeares, <hi>5 pag. 24</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>fifth <hi>300</hi> yeares, <hi>6 pag. 30</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sedition of
<list>
                        <item>Puritans</item>
                        <item>Papiſts
<list>
                              <item>Concord in the matter, of ſedition. <hi>cap. 7. p. 36</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>Diſcord in the manner of ſedition. <hi>cap. 7. p. 36</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>Danger of their doctrine to
<list>
                                    <item>Prince, <hi>cap. 8. p. 43.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>People, <hi>cap. 8. p. 43.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>Puritan-Ieſuitiſme, or the generall conſent of the principall Puritans and Ieſuits, againſt Kings, from the yeare <hi>1536.</hi> vntill the yeare <hi>1602.</hi> out of the moſt authentique Authors. <hi>cap. 8. p. 46</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:14168:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14168:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14168:9"/>
            <head>The firſt Chapter prooveth by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Scripture, that Kings are not puniſhable by man, but reſerued to the iudgement of God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>INGS haue their authoritie from God<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note>, and are his Vicegerents in earth<note n="b" place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note>, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iuſtice and iudgement for him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſonnes of men<note n="c" place="margin">2. Chron. 19.6.</note>. All ſubiects (as well Prelates and Nobles, as the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour people) are forbidden with the <hi>tongue,</hi> to reuile Kings<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 22.28.</note>, with the <hi>heart,</hi> to thinke ill of them<note n="e" place="margin">Eccl. 10.20.</note>, or with the <hi>hand,</hi> to reſiſt them<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note>. The great King of heauen doth impart his owne name vnto his <hi>Lieftenants</hi> the Kings of the earth: and calleth them <hi>Gods,</hi> with an <hi>ego dixi</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.</note>, whoſe word is <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen:</hi> with this onely difference, that theſe <hi>Gods ſhall die like men</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 82.7.</note>, and fall like other Princes. Wherefore <hi>Nathan</hi> the man of God, muſt reprooue <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">2. Sam. 12.7</note>, that he may repent, and be ſaued. And the Sages, Iudges, and Nobles (without feare or flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) muſt aduiſe and direct <hi>Roboam</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Reg 12.7</note>. Other attempts againſt Kings, the King of Kings hath neither commanded in his law, nor permitted in his Goſpel.<note place="margin">Apolog. Dauid cap. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe) nullis legibus tenebatur, &amp;c.</hi> Dauid though he were an adulterer, and an homicide, was tied to no law: for Kings are free from bonds, and can by no compulſion of law, be drawne to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, beeing freed by the power of gouernment. Thus farre <hi>Ambr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14168:10"/>
               <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was rather a monſter, then a man: after the ſpirit of God had forſaken him, and the euill ſpirit was come vpon him<note n="m" place="margin">1. Sam 16.14.</note>. There were not many ſinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, Man, or Nature, wherein he tranſgreſſed not; yet his exceſſe was puniſhed, neither by the Sacerdotall Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, nor the ſecular Senate: <hi>Who can lay his hand on the Lords Annointed, and be guiltleſſe</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">1. Sam. 16.9.</note>? The very Annointment was the cauſe of Sauls immunitie from all humane coercion: as <hi>Augustine</hi> affirmeth,<note place="margin">Aug. contr. lit. Petil. l. 2. 148.</note> 
               <hi>Quero ſinon habebat, Saul ſacramenti ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitatem, quid ineo Dauid venerabatur?</hi> If Saul had not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of the Sacrament, I aske what it was that Dauid reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced in him? he honoured Saul for the ſacred and holy vnction, while he liued: and reuenged his death. Yea, he was troubled and trembled at the heart, becauſe he had cut off a lappe of Sauls garment. Loe, Saul had no innocencie, and yet he had holineſſe: not of life, but of vnction. So farre <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who queſtioned <hi>Dauid</hi> for his murther and adulterie? who cenſured <hi>Salomon</hi> for his idolatrie? though their crimes were capitall by the law of God. After that kingdome was diuided, all the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and moſt of the Kings of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> were notorious idolaters: yet during thoſe kingdomes, which endured aboue 200. yeares, no Prieſt did chalenge, no States-men did claime power from the higheſt, to puniſh or depoſe their Princes. And the Prophets perſwaded all men to obey, and endure thoſe idolatrous Princes, whoſe impietie they reprooued with the loſſe of their liues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christ</hi> fled when the people would haue made him a King<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 6.15.</note>. He paied tribute for himſelfe and <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 17.27.</note>. When the queſtion was propounded concerning the <hi>Emperours</hi> ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, he concluded for <hi>Caeſar</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 22.21.</note>. And ſtanding to receiue the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14168:10"/>
iudgement of death before <hi>Pilate,</hi> he acknowledged his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be of God<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 19.11.</note>. This <hi>Sauiour of Mankind,</hi> whoſe actions ſhould be our inſtruction, did neuer attempt to change that gouernment, or to diſplace thoſe gouernours, which were directly repugnant to the ſcope of <hi>reformation</hi> that he ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> did indeede reprooue king Herod with a <hi>Non licet</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mark. 6.18</note>, but he taught not the ſouldiers to leaue his ſeruice, or by ſtrife and impatience, to wind themſelues out of the band of allegiance, wherein the <hi>law</hi> had left them, and the <hi>Goſpel</hi> found them<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 3.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> deliuered vnto the Church the doctrine of obedience and patience, which they had learned by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and obſerued by the practiſe of our Lord Chriſt. <hi>Peter</hi> commandeth obedience to all manner of men in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<note n="g" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.</note>. <hi>Paul</hi> forbiddeth reſiſtance againſt any power<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 23.1, 2, 3, 4.</note>. And <hi>S. Iude</hi> maketh it blaſphemie, to reuile gouernment, or to ſpeak euill of gouernours<note n="i" place="margin">Iude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. <hi>If therefore an Angel from heauen preach otherwiſe, then they haue deliuered, let him be accurſed</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>The ſecond Chapter prooueth the ſame by the Fathers of the firſt <hi>300.</hi> yeares.</head>
            <p>THe true Church, which had the ſpirit of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to diſcerne the voice of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from the voice of a <hi>ſtranger,</hi> neuer taught, neuer practiſed, neuer vſed or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued other weapons, then ſalt teares, and humble praiers againſt the <hi>Paganiſme, hereſie, apoſtacie,</hi> and <hi>tyrannie</hi> of earthly Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuſtinus Martyr, Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> ſhall beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for 300. yeares, wherein the Kings and Potentates of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14168:11"/>
the earth, bathed themſelues in the blood of innocents, and profeſſed enmitie againſt Chriſt and his ſeruants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ad inquiſitionem veſtram, Chriſtianos nos eſſe profitemur, &amp;c.</hi> At your inquiſition, we profeſſe our ſelues to be Chriſtians, though we knowe death to be the guerdon of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (ſaith <hi>Iuſtine Martyr</hi> to the Emperour <hi>Antoninus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccund. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. ad Ant. Imp. p. 113.</note>) did we expect an earthly kingdome, we would denie our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that eſcaping death, we might in time attaine our expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation: But we feare not perſecution, which haue not our hope fixed on the things of this life, becauſe we are certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, that we muſt die. As for the preſeruation of publique peace, we Chriſtians yeeld to you (O Emperour) more helpe and aſſiſtance, then any other men. For we teach, that no euill doer, no couetous man, nor ſeditious, that lieth in wait for blood, can haue acceſſe to God: And that euerie man doth paſſe to life or death, according to the merit of his deeds: Thus farre he.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tertull. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Scap.</note>We (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi> to <hi>Scapula</hi> the Viceroy of <hi>Carthage</hi>) are defamed, for ſeditious againſt the Imperial Maieſtie: Yet were the Chriſtians neuer found to be <hi>Albinians, Nigrians,</hi> or <hi>Caſsians, (Albinus, Niger, and Caſſius were traytors againſt Marcus Antonius, Commodus, Pertinax, and Seuerus the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours</hi>) but they that ſware by the Emperours dietie, the very day before: they that vowed and offred ſacrifice for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours health, are found to be the Emperors enemies. A Chriſtian, is enemie to no man, much leſſe to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: knowing, that the Emperiall maieſtie, is ordained of God, and therefore neceſſarily to be loued, reuerenced, and honoured, whoſe proſperitie, together with the welfare of all the Romane Empire they deſire ſo long as the world ſtandeth. We doe therefore honour the Emperour, in ſuch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14168:11"/>
ſort, as is lawfull for vs, and expedient for him: we reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence him as a mortall man, next vnto God, of whom he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all his authoritie, onely ſubiect to God, and ſo we make him, ſoueraigne ouer all, in that, we make him ſubiect, but to God alone: So farre <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſheweth many good reaſons, for the patience of the Saints, in his booke againſt <hi>Demetrianus.</hi> God (ſaith he) is the reuenger of his ſervants, when they are annoied. Wherefore no Chriſtian when he is apprehended, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt or revenge himſelfe againſt your vniuſt violence, though the number of our people be very great. The confidence we haue, that God will reward, doth confirme our patience, the guiltleſſe giue way to the guilty, the innocent reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with their vndeſerued puniſhment, and tortures, beeing certainely aſſured that the wrong done to vs, ſhall not be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewarded. The more iniurie we ſuffer, the more iuſt and grieuous ſhall Gods vengeance be on them that perſecute vs. It is therefore cleare and manifeſt, that the plagues which come downe from Gods indignation, doe not come tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough vs poore perſecuted Chriſtians, but from him whom we ſerue, for the wrong done vnto vs. So farre <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As many as liued according to Chriſts inſtitution, did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reuile the gouernement of Tyrants, much leſſe by force reſiſt their violence, following the patience of Chriſt, who could by his owne power, the might of his Angels, or the ſtrength of his creatures, haue at the firſt withſtood, or, at the laſt reuenged, the iniurie of the people, the buffer of the Prieſts ſeruant, the ſcorne of <hi>Herod,</hi> the iudgement of <hi>Pilate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10 15. Io <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the violence of the ſouldiers. He yeelded himſelfe pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to death, to teach all his diſciples, that an iniurie done by authoritie, is patiently to be endured, not forcibly to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14168:12"/>
repelled. As ſoone alſo as <hi>Paul</hi> became a Chriſtian, his ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and bloody ſpirit, which he had learned of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, was changed into a deſire of peace, and quietneſſe. He honoured the heathen Magiſtrates, as <hi>Agrippa, Faelix,</hi> and <hi>Liſias,</hi> ratifying his doctrine, by the practiſe of his life. I knowe that Cardinall <hi>Alane,</hi> Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine, Ficlerus, Simancha,</hi> and other vpholders of the Papall tyrannie, that <hi>Stephanus Iunius, Franciſcus Hottomanus, Georgius Buchananus,</hi> and other pillars of the <hi>Puritane</hi> anarchie, doe anſwear, that the Church then, as it were ſwathed in the bonds of weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, had not ſtrength ſufficient to make powerfull reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. But theſe <hi>Fathers</hi> that then liued, doe conuince them, and all other ſectaries of falſhood, by making demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of the ſtrength and potencie of the godly Chriſtians, in caſe they would haue put their forces to the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt proofe. Seeing that all publike places, as Courts, Camps, Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Cities, and countrey villages, were ſtored and furniſhed with men of that profeſſion and qualitie, as doth moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare by the words of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his Apolegeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call defence of the Chriſtians: <hi>Vna nox pauculis faculis, &amp;c.</hi> One night with a few firebrands, would yeeld vs ſufficient reuenge, if it were lawfull for vs to requite euill for euill. But God forbid, that Chriſtians ſhould either reuenge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with humane fire, or be grieued to ſuffer that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are tried. Were we diſpoſed, not to practiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret reuenge, but to profeſſe open hoſtilitie, ſhould we want number of men, or force of armes? Are the Moores, or the Parthians, or any one nation whatſoeuer, more in number then we, that are ſpread ouer all the world? We are not of you, and yet we haue filled all the places and roomes which you haue. Your Cities, Ilands, Caſtles, townes, aſſemblies,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14168:12"/>
your Tents, Tribes, and Wards; yea, the Imperiall Pallace, Senate, and ſeats of iudgement. For what warre, were not we, able and readie, though we were fewer in number then you, that go to our Martyrdome ſo willingly? if it were not more lawfull in our religion to be ſlaine, then to ſlay? we could without armour, not by rebelling againſt you, but by departing from you, doe you diſpleaſure enough, euen with our ſeparation. For if ſo great a multitude, as we are, ſhould breake out from you, in any other corner of the world, the loſſe of ſo many citizens would ſhame and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you. You would feare, to ſee your ſelues left ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, euen amazed, as among the dead. You ſhould then ſee, ſilence and deſolation euerie where. You would haue many more enemies, then inhabitants. Whereas now, you haue fewer enemies, becauſe of the multitude of your citizens, that are almoſt all Chriſtians. <hi>Haec Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus.</hi> We ſee by theſe three witneſſes, that the Church of God, in the firſt 300. yeares wanted, neither number of men, ſtrength, nor courage to reſiſt perſecution, and to haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed the Chriſtian faith, if that courſe had beene lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: but becauſe their Lord had giuen them no ſword to ſtrike withall, they choſe rather to be crowned <hi>Martyrs,</hi> for their religion, then to be puniſhed as traytors for rebellion. What number of men, what ſtrength of armes had the Church (thinke you) the next 300. yeares after it had beene backed by Princes, defended by lawes, prouoked by honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable fauours, to profeſſe Chriſtianitie? Yet all that while, the ſeruants of God, neither did nor would reſiſt Apoſtaſie, Hereſie, or Tyrannie: but yeelded their liues, with all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, though they wanted neither meanes nor multitude, conuenient for any warres, as the next chapter by, pregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14168:13"/>
demonſtration, ſhall ſhewe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>The third Chapter prooueth by the Fathers, of the ſecond <hi>300.</hi> yeares, that the pleaſure of Princes, muſt be endured with patience, when their decrees cannot be obeyed with a good Conſcience.</head>
            <p>THe next 300. yeares, the Chriſtians did as patiently endure Hereſie, Apoſtaſie, and Tyrannie, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious triall of their faith, and the eternall reward of their patience. Whereof we haue a cloud of witneſſes, namely, <hi>Hoſius, Liberius, Athanaſius, Hilarius, Baſilius Magnus, Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Nazianzenus, Lucifer Calaritanus, Cyrillus Alexandrinus, Optatus Milevitanus, Ambroſius, Auguſtinus, Chryſoſtomus, Leo</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoſius</hi> was a famous confeſſor in the Church, before <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the great a worthie Biſhop during that Emperours raigne, and after his death greatly eſteemed of all good men, yea euen of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Arrian Emperour himſelfe, for his old age, great experience, excellent learning, and good conuerſation. When this worthie Prelate, was commanded by the Emperour, to ſubſcribe to the condemnation of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> he returned to the Imperiall Maieſtie, this ſtout, Conſtant, Chriſtian, and dutifull anſwear; <hi>Ego confeſſionis munus implevi primum, cum perſecutio moueretur, ab avo tuo Maximiniano:</hi> I was then a confeſſor, when your grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Maximinian</hi> perſecuted the Church.<note place="margin">Obſequere &amp; ſcithe contra Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n qui enim contra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llum ſcribit the plane nob ſcum, &amp;c.</note> And if you doe now raiſe perſecution, I am readie to endure any thing, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then betray the truth and ſhed innocent blood. I do not like your manner of writing againſt <hi>Athanaſius:</hi> Ceaſe from it, be not of the Arrian opinion: Giue no eare to the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14168:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Biſhops: beleeue me rather, that for age might be your grandfather. Leaue off I beſeech you, and call to mind, that you are a mortall man. Feare that dreadfull day of iudgement. Enterpoſe not your ſelfe (O Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) into the eccleſiaſticall ſervice, neither command vs in this kind, to condemne the innocent: but learne ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vs. God hath entruſted your Maieſtie with the Empire, and committed vnto vs, the ſeruice of the Church: he that with an envious eie, maligneth your imperiall ſoueraigntie, contradicteth the ordinance of God. Take heede (O Prince) leaſt drawing to your ſelfe the right of the Church, you become guiltie of grieuous tranſgreſſion. It is written,<note place="margin">Hoſius apud Atham ad ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litariam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam agentes.</note> Giue vnto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that appertaine to God: it is therefore, neither lawfull for vs Prieſts, to vſurpe your kingdome: nor for you Princes, to meddle with the ſacred ſeruice, and ſacrifices of the Church. Thus farre <hi>Hoſius.</hi> You ſee the grounds, that this good Biſhop ſtood vpon: rather reſolued to ſuffer any death or torture, then by his conſent to betray the truth, or to condemne the guiltleſſe. He admoniſheth freely, and reprooueth ſharply, he offreth his life to the Princes pleaſure: It was farre from his meaning, to reuile the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred maieſtie, or to ſtirre vp any rebellion, againſt this hereticall Emperour, which infringed the <hi>Canons</hi> of the Church, without all regard of truth or equitie, to ſerue the humors of the Arrians, and to wreck his anger on them all, which yeelded not to that hereſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liberius</hi> a Biſhop of Rome, did neither excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate nor depoſe this wicked Emperour <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> but appeared at his commaund, and endured his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14168:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to the admiration of the Arrians, and the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Chriſtians, as we finde in <hi>Athanaſius, Trahitur Liberius ad imperatorem, &amp;c. Liberius</hi> was haled to the Emperour, when he came to his preſence he ſpake freely, Ceaſe (ſaid he) O Emperour, to perſecute the Chriſtians, goe not about, by any meanes, to bring hereticall impietie into the Church of God.<note place="margin">Liberius quo ſupra apud Athan.</note> We are readie, rather to endure any torture, then to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Arrians. Compell vs not to become enemies vnto Chriſt. Fight not againſt him (we beſeech you) that hath beſtowed the Empire vpon you. Render not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie to him for his grace, perſecute them not which beleeue in him, leaſt you heare, <hi>it is hard for thee to kicke againſt the pricke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 9.5.</note> Oh would to God you did ſo heare it that you might (as Paul did) beleeue it. Loe we are at hand, and come to your preſence, before our enemies the Arrians can inuent any thing to enforme againſt vs, we haſtened to come at your commande, though we were aſſured of baniſhment: that we might abide our puniſhment, before any crime could be obiected, much leſſe prooued againſt vs. Whereby it may appeare, that all Chriſtians are (as we now be) vndeſeruedly puniſhed, and the crimes laid to their charge not true but fained by ſycophancy or deceitfull ſubtilty. Thus ſpake <hi>Liberius;</hi> &amp; euery man admired his reſolution: but the Emperour for anſwer commanded him to baniſhment. Thus farre he.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Liberius</hi> had not learned the language of his ſucceſſor <hi>Pius Quinius,</hi> when he bellowed againſt our late Queene, nor that principle of the <hi>Puritanes,</hi> that the inferior officer may vſe force of armes againſt the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14168:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
cheife Magiſtrate that ſhall become a tyrant <hi>(whereof euery ſeditious ſectarie will be iudge)</hi> and not onely defend himſelfe, and his owne people, but alſo any other that ſhall flie vnto him.<note place="margin">Poliria Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. l. 6. c. 3.</note> Which opinion <hi>Lambertus Danaus</hi> auoucheth, contrarie to the Law, the Goſpel, and the generall conſent of all orthodoxall Fathers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hilarius,</hi> a Biſhop of France,<note place="margin">Hilarius ad Imperatote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Conſtant.</note> wrote the ſame time to this ſame Emperour in moſt humble manner, <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fica natura tua domine beatiſſime Auguſte:</hi> Your milde na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, moſt bleſſed Emperour, agreeing with your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious diſpoſition, and the mercie which floweth aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, from the fountaine of your fatherly godlineſſe, doe aſſure vs, that we ſhall obtaine our deſire. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, not onely with words, but alſo with teares, that the catholique Churches, be no longer oppreſſed with greeuous iniuries, and endure intollerable perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, and contumelies, and that (which is moſt ſhamefull) euen of our brethren. Let your Clemencie prouide, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Surely, if it had then beene knowne, that the Pope, by his abſolute power or indirect authoritie, could haue puniſhed or depoſed kings, which the Papiſts auouch, or for the Peeres or the people to haue done it, which the <hi>Puritanes</hi> affirme, ſome of theſe olde Biſhops, would haue preſſed that point againſt this hereticall Prince, which abuſed his ſword, to the blaſpheming of Chriſt, the murthering of the Saints, the ſeducing of many thouſand ſoules: by ſtrengthening, maintaining, and eſtabliſhing the Arrian error. But they tooke it to be no Chriſtian mans part, to beare armour (no not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue) againſt his Prince, though neuer ſo wicked,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14168:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
cruell or vngodly.</p>
            <p>Holy <hi>Athanaſius</hi> confeſſeth the power of Kings to be of God, and their impietie not to be puniſhed by man. <hi>Sicut in toto mundo Deus rex eſt &amp; imperator &amp; poteſtatem exeroet in omnibus:</hi> As God is King and Emperour ouer all the world, and exerciſeth his power in all creatures: ſo the King and Prince is ouer all earthly men, and doth by his abſolute power,<note place="margin">Ad Antioch. queſt. 55.</note> what he will, euen as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>haec ille.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When it was obiected againſt this reuerend father Athanaſius, that he had incenſed <hi>Conſtans</hi> the religious Emperour of the Weſt, againſt <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behalfe of the perſecuted Chriſtians:<note place="margin">Apolog. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than. ad Conſtant.</note> he cleared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from that accuſation, in an Apologie to the ſaide Emperour <hi>Constantius.</hi> The Lord (ſaith he) is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and his annointed your brother, that I neuer made mention of your Maieſtie for any euill, before your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of bleſſed memorie, that religious Emperour <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans.</hi> I did neuer incite him againſt you, as theſe Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans doe ſlaunder me, but whenſoeuer I had acceſſe vnto him, I recounted your gracious inclination. God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, what mention I made of your godly diſpoſition. Giue me leaue and pardon (moſt courteous Emperour) to ſpeake the truth. That ſeruant of God <hi>Conſtans,</hi> was not eaſily drawne to giue eare to any man in this kind. I was neuer in ſuch credit with him, that I durſt ſpeake of any ſuch matter, or derogate from one brother before an other, or talke reprochfully of one Emperour, in the hearing of an other. I am not ſo madde, neither haue I forgotten the voice of God, which ſaith, Curſe not the King in thine heart, and backbite not the mightie in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14168:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſecrets of thy chamber: for the birds of the ayre ſhall tell it, and the winged foule ſhall bewray thee. If then, the things that be ſpoken in ſecret againſt Princes, can not be hid: is there any likelihood, that I in the Emperours preſence, and before ſo many, as continually attended his perſon, would ſay any thing otherwiſe then well of your Maieſtie? Thus farre <hi>Athanaſ.</hi> This is ſounder and ſeemelier doctrine for ſubiects, then that which <hi>Henrie Garnet,</hi> and <hi>Robert Teſmond,</hi> taught ſome Romiſh catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like gentlemen of <hi>England,</hi> who imployed <hi>Thomas Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> into <hi>Spaine,</hi> in the moneth of December, <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1601. to make requeſt to the Spaniſh king, in the behalfe and names of the Engliſh Pope-catholikes,<note place="margin">L. Cooke in his ſpeach at Garnets ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment.</note> that he would ſend an armie hither into England, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of their Catholique cauſe; and to promiſe, that the forces of the <hi>Papists</hi> here, ſhould be readie to doe him ſeruice againſt the late <hi>Queene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſelfe ſame doctrine of ſedition, was publiſhed in the yeare after, <hi>viz. ann. Dom.</hi> 1602. by <hi>Gulielmus Bucanus,</hi> a man of no meane eſteeme among the <hi>Puritans,</hi> and that, at the earneſt requeſt of <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Gonlartius,</hi> the chiefeſt Miniſters of the Chutch of <hi>Geneva,</hi> (if the author himſelfe belie them not,) whoſe words are as followeth: <hi>Subditis ſi fit publica &amp; manifeſta ſaevitia, licet fieri ſupplices, implorare auxilia ab alijs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſuſcipere corum defenſionem alijs regibus licet:</hi> Subiects, when they endure publique and manifeſt wrong, may lawfully become ſuppliants to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne ſtates, and craue their ayde againſt their Princes: and other Kings ought to take vpon them their defence and protection. So farre <hi>Bucan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Subiects muſt ſquare their ſubiection, according to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14168:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the rule of Gods word, not after the affection and fancies of men.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> commanded <hi>Doeg</hi> to murther 85. Prieſts, to deſtroy their citie, men, women, and children with the edge of the ſword. Did <hi>Dauid,</hi> for whome they were ſlaine, when he had <hi>Saul</hi> in his power, take reuenge, or ſuffer his ſeruants to doe it, when they were readie and offered themſelues to ſlay <hi>Saul? Dauid</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. Sam. 11.4.17.</note> defiled <hi>Vrias</hi> his bed, and cauſed him to be killed: Did <hi>Abſolon</hi> well, to conſpire againſt him, that was both a murtherer and an adulterer? <hi>Salomon</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 Reg. 11.8.</note> brought into the land many ſtrange wiues, and as many <hi>different religions</hi> into the Church: Did the high Prieſt, the Peeres, the Prophets, or the people, offer to chaſtice or depoſe him? <hi>Achab</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1 Reg. 11.8.9.</note> ſuffered <hi>Iezabel</hi> to put <hi>Naboth</hi> to death, and to kill the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: Did <hi>Elias</hi> depoſe him, intice his ſubiects to rebell againſt him, or implore foraigne aide to deſtroy him? <hi>Herod</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mar 6.27. Act. 12.24.</note> beheaded <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> killed Iames, impriſoned <hi>Peter,</hi> and would haue ſlaine him alſo, if he had not beene deliuered by an Angel: Did <hi>Peter</hi> take vengeance on <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> which he might haue done with a word, as well as on<note n="f" place="margin">Act 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Ananias?</hi> No: he did leaue him to the Lord, whoſe iudgement inſued in moſt<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 12.23.</note> fearefull manner. In a word, wicked Princes haue neuer beene lawfully puniſhed by Prelates, Potentates, or people of their kingdome, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> averre: but muſt be reſerued to the iudgement of God, as the <hi>Protestants</hi> affirme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> in his oration at the funerall of <hi>S. Baſil,</hi> reporteth, that the Emperours Deputie in <hi>Pontus,</hi> commanded <hi>S. Baſil</hi> to put out a widow, that had taken ſanctuarie to ſaue her ſelfe from forced mariage.<note place="margin">Baſilius mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop (not willing to violate the Eccleſiaſticall laws gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14168:16"/>
by the Imperiall Maieſtie) refuſed ſo to doe. The go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor called the Biſhop before him, threatned to whip him, and to teare his fleſh with iron hookes: the people hearing that indignitie offered to the Biſhop, fell to an vprore, and would haue ſlaine the Lieftenant, <hi>had not that innocent man of God, with much adoe, ſtaied that furious tumult, and deliuered his perſecutor from that perill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Monodia Nazian, inter opuſcula Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilij fol. 95.</note> 
               <hi>to whoſe pleaſure he did afterward ſubmit himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> for his admirable learning cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>diuine,</hi> writeth of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata-Emperours death: <hi>Iulian</hi> was puniſhed by the mercie of God, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the teares of Chriſtian men: which teares were many, and ſhed of many, for that they had no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, againſt that perſecutor. Thus farre <hi>Nazian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. orat. cont. I dian.</note> This godly father liued vnder fiue Emperours, <hi>Conſtantius, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus, Valens, Valentinianus,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> in all which time, he could find no remedie againſt the tyrannie, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, and apoſtaſie of Princes, beſide prayers and teares: The deuill of hell had not as yet hatched the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>propriè</hi> and <hi>impropriè, directè</hi> and <hi>indirectè, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter</hi> and <hi>ſecundum quid, abſolutè &amp; in ordine ad ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> wherewith the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> doe fill the ſchooles with cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous evaſions, the Church with erroneous ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and many Chriſtian ſtates with tragicall ſedition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucifer Calaritanus</hi> in ſundrie bookes againſt <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> vſeth many immodeſt and diſloiall ſpeeches: but he perſwaded not the Pope to depoſe him, the ſtate to puniſh him, the people to rebell againſt him, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine aide to ſuppreſſe him, but threatned him with the dreadfull puniſhment of God. He that (in the feruency of zeale) durſt call ſo cruell an Emperour, <hi>Theefe, Church-robber,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14168:17"/>
Murtherer, Beaſt, Hangman, Heretique, Apostata, Idolator, the forerunner of Antichriſt, and Antichriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> would ſurely haue encouraged the Pope, the Peeres or the people, to haue remoued that euill king, and placed a better in his ſtead: if there had beene any ſuch opinion in thoſe daies, as our moderne <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi> beare now the world in hand. As this father, in his writings, kept not the modeſtie of the other fathers, which liued in that age vnder <hi>Conſtantius:</hi> ſo he did not continue in the vnitie of the catholique Church. <hi>Lucifer</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe) deuided himſelfe from our communion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>though he were baniſhed with vs for our religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was commanded, to deliuer vp his Church in <hi>Myllaine</hi> to <hi>Maxentius</hi> an <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhop, he declared his reſolution in a ſermon to the people: which were verie ſorie for his departure. <hi>Quid turbamini? vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens nunquam vos deſeram:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nter epiſtol. 32.33</note> Why are you troubed? I will neuer willingly depart from you. If I be compelled, I haue no waie to reſiſt: I can ſorrow, I can weepe, I can ſigh, my teares are my weapons againſt Souldiours, Armour, Gothes: ſuch is the munition of a preiſt: by any other meanes, then teares, I neither ought nor can reſiſt: ſo farre <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> Not diſabilitie but dutie, not want of ſtrength and martiall forces, but a reuerend re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Emperours Maieſtie, commanded by the law of God, kept this bleſſed <hi>Ambroſe</hi> from reſiſting. For he might eaſily haue wrought the churches liberty, his owne ſaftie, and the Arrians calamitie by the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe of the Emperour, through the force of the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon in that Citie, which refuſed, to attend the Prince to any other Church, then that wherein <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14168:17"/>
The ſtout and peremptorie anſwer of the Captaines and ſouldiers, is thus reported by <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in an epiſtle to <hi>Marcellina,</hi> a religious woman.<note place="margin">Epiſtol. 33.</note> 
               <hi>Si prodire vellet haberet copiam ſe preſto futuros:</hi> The Emperour may goe at his pleaſure, they would be readie to attend him, if he would goe to the catholike aſſemblies: or otherwiſe, they would keepe on their way to that Congregation, wherein <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> was: <hi>Thus farre the ſouldiers.</hi> They refuſed (as you ſee) to obey, and preferred <hi>Gods</hi> true ſeruice, before the <hi>Emperours</hi> fauour: they reuiled not his ſacred perſon, they reſiſted not his ſoueraigne power, but yeelded themſelues to his mercy and pleaſure, to ſaue their ſoules from Gods wrath and diſpleaſure, as we find in the ſame epiſtle. <hi>Vnum Iob miraturus aſcenderam,</hi> I went to Church to extoll the patience of Iob,<note place="margin">Epiſt. eadem.</note> where I found euerie one of my hearers, a Iob, worthie to be extolled. In euerie one of you Iob is reuiued, in each of you his patience, and vertue ſhined, what could be ſaid better by Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an men, then that which the holy Ghoſt this day ſpake in you? We beſeech (O Emperour,) we offer not to fight, we feare not to die, we entreat your clemencie. Oh it was ſeemely for Chriſtian ſouldiers, to deſire the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie of peace and faith, and to be conſtant in truth, euen vnto death: Thus farre <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> relateth the ſame of the Chriſtian ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, vnder <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata-Emperour: <hi>Iulianus extitit imperator infidelis,</hi> Iulian was an vnbeleeuing Emperour, was he not an Apoſtata? an oppreſſor, and an Idolater? Chriſtian ſouldiers ſerued that vnbeleeuing Emperour. When they came to the cauſe of Chriſt, they would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge no Lord but him that was in heauen: when
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14168:18"/>
they were commanded to adore Idoles, and to offer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, they preferred. God before their Prince. But when he called vpon them to warre, &amp; bad them inuade any nation, they preſently obeyed. They did diſtinguiſh their eternall Lord, from the temporall king, yet they ſubmitted themſelues to their temporal Lord, for his ſake that was their eternall king:<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 124.</note> So farre he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Optatus Milevitanus,</hi> is another pregnant witneſſe: <hi>Cum ſuper Imperatorem nemo ſit niſi ſolus Deus.</hi> Seeing there is no man aboue the Emperour, beſide God alone, which made the Emperour: <hi>Donatus,</hi> by advancing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aboue the Emperour,<note place="margin">De ſchiſm. Donatiſt. l. 3.</note> doth exceede the bounds of humanitie, and maketh himſelfe a God rather then man, in that he feareth and reuerenceth him not, whom all men ſhould honour, next after God. So farre <hi>Optat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Com. in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. Ioh. l. 12. c. 36.</note>Saint <hi>Cyril</hi> is of the ſame iudgement. <hi>Cui legis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaericatores liberare licet niſi legis ipſius authori?</hi> Who can acquit them that breake the law, from tranſgreſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the law-giuer? as we ſee by experience, in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſtates, no man can without danger, breake the law, but kings themſelues, in whom the crime of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarication hath no place. For it was wiſely ſaid of one, that it is a wicked preſumption, to ſay to a king, <hi>Thou doeſt amiſſe.</hi> So farre he.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In 1. epiſt. ad Timoth c. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note>And alſo Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome.</hi> What meaneth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle (ſaith he) to require prayers and ſupplications, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interceſſions, and thankſgiuing, to be made for all men? he requireth this to be done in the daily ſeruice of the Church, and the perpetuall rite of diuine religion. For all the faithfull do knowe, in what manner prayers are powred out before the Lord morning and euening, for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14168:18"/>
all the world: euen for kings, and euery man in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Some man will (peradventure) ſay, that, <hi>for all,</hi> muſt be vnderſtood of all the faithfull. Which cannot be the Apoſtles meaning, as may appeare by the words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz. for Kings:</hi> ſeeing that kings, neither did then, nor in many ages after, ſerue the liuing God: but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued obſtinately in infidelitie, which by courſe of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion they had receiued: Thus farre <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> Our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne reformers teach vs that which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> neither knewe nor beleeued,<note place="margin">See the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face before Baſilic. Dor.</note> that wicked Princes are not to be prayed for, but to be reſiſted, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>When the faction of <hi>Eutiches</hi> had preuailed againſt the Catholikes, <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt, had no other remedie then prayers to God, ſighes, teares, and petitions to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: <hi>Omnes partium noſtrarum eccleſiae, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſtol. 24. ad Theodoſ. Imperat.</note> All the Churches of theſe parts, all we Prieſts, euen with ſighs, and teares, beſeech your Maieſtie, to command a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Synode to be held in Italie, that all offences bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remooued, there may remaine, neither error in faith, nor diuiſion in loue. Fauour the catholiques, grant liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to protect the faith againſt heretiques, defend the ſtate of the Church from ruine, that Chriſt his right-hand may ſupport your Empire: Thus farre <hi>Leo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great was accuſed for the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a Biſhop in priſon, he wrote to one <hi>Sabinianus,</hi> to cleare him to the Emperour and Empreſſe. <hi>Breuiter ſuggeras ſereniſſimis dominis meis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. l. 7. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 1.</note> You may briefly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme my ſoueraigne Lord and Ladie, that if I their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, would haue buſied my ſelfe with the death of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> that nation would by this time haue had, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kings, nor Dukes, nor Earles, &amp; ſhould haue bin in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14168:19"/>
great confuſion and diuiſion: but becauſe I ſtood in awe of God, I was euer afraid, to meddle with the ſhedding of any mans blood: ſo farre <hi>Gregorie.</hi> Theſe <hi>Lombards</hi> were Pagans, invaders of the countrey, ranſackers of the citie, perſecutors of the Saints, robbers of the Church, oppreſſors of the poore: whom <hi>Gregorie</hi> the firſt, might, and would not deſtroy, <hi>quia deum timuit,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he <hi>feared God.</hi> It is verie like, that his ſucceſſor <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> the ſeauenth, feared neither <hi>God nor man,</hi> when he erected the papall croiſier againſt the regall ſcepter, and read the ſentence of depriuation, againſt the Emperour <hi>Henrie: Ego authoritate apoſtolica, &amp;c.</hi> I by my power apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall, doe bereaue <hi>Henrie</hi> of the Germaine kingdom, and do depriue him of all ſubiection of Chriſtian men, abſoluing all men, from the allegiance, which they haue ſworne vnto him. And that <hi>Rodolph,</hi> whom the Peeres of the Empire haue elected, may gouerne the kingdome: I grant all men, that ſhall ſerue him againſt the Emperor, forgiueneſſe of their ſinnes, in this life and in the life to come.<note place="margin">Carol. Sigon. de Regno I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. lib. 9. in vita Hen. 3.</note> As I haue for his pride deiected Henrie from the royall dignitie, ſo I doe exalt Rodolph for his humilitie, to that place of authoritie: Thus farre <hi>Gregor.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Benno Card in vit. Greg. 7</note>It is no wonder, that <hi>Gregorie</hi> his chaire claue a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as ſome writers affirme, at the giuing of this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: becauſe the proud Pope, and his wicked ſentence, were too heauie a burthen for <hi>Peters</hi> ſtoole of humilitie to beare.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14168:19"/>
            <head>The fourth Chapter prooveth the Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Kings by the Fathers of the third <hi>300.</hi> yeares.</head>
            <p>AFter the death of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeare of our Lord 604. <hi>Sabinianus</hi> did ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede him, who liued but one yeare, after whome came <hi>Boniface</hi> the 3. which obtained of <hi>Phocas</hi> to be called <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall Biſhop;</hi> ſince that time, <hi>perijt virtus Imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; pietas Pontificum,</hi> the Emperours waxed <hi>weake,</hi> and the Biſhops <hi>wicked.</hi> What the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thoſe Fathers then was, concerning ſubiection to wicked Kings, I will make euident by the teſtimonie of <hi>Gregorius Turo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis, Iſidorus, Damaſcenus, Beda, Fulgentius, Leo</hi> 4. and the Fathers aſſembled in a <hi>Councell</hi> at <hi>Toledo</hi> in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregorie Turonenſis</hi> acknowledgeth ſuch an abſolute power in <hi>Childericke,</hi> a moſt wicked king of France, as was free from all controll of man.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. lib 5. cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Si quis de nobis (Rex) iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae limites tranſcendere voluerit, &amp;c.</hi> If any one of vs (O King) doe paſſe the bounds of iuſtice, you haue power to correct him, but if you exceede your limit, who ſhall chaſtice you? We may ſpeake vnto you; if you liſt not to harken, who can condemne you, but that <hi>Great God,</hi> who hath pronounced himſelfe to be righteouſnes? <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctenus ille.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſidorus</hi> ſaith no leſſe for the immunitie of the Kings of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Let all earthly Princes know, that they ſhall giue account of the Church, which Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their protection. Yea, whether the peace and diſcipline Eccleſiaſticall be aduanced, by faithfull Kings,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14168:20"/>
or diſſolued by the vnfaithfull, he will require a recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at their hands, which hath left his Church in their power. So farre <hi>Iſidor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Damaſcene</hi> pleadeth not onely for the exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of wicked kings themſelues, but alſo of their Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.<note place="margin">Parallel. lib. 1. c. 21.</note> The gouernours (ſaith he) which Kings create, though they be wicked, though they be theeues, though they be vniuſt, or otherwiſe tainted with any crime, muſt be regarded. We may not contemne them, for their impietie; but muſt reuerence them, becauſe of their authoritie, by whome they were appointed our gouernours. So farre he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith, that no kinde of ſedition can ſtand with religion. <hi>Cum pro noſtra fide libere reſpondemus, &amp;c.</hi> When we anſwer freely for our profeſſion, we ought not to be taxed with the leaſt ſuſpition of diſobedience or contumely, ſeeing we are not vnmindfull of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall dignitie, and doe know, that we muſt feare God, and honour the King, according to the doctrine of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulgent. ad Thraſim reg.</note> Giue to each one his due, feare to whome feare, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to whome honour appertaineth. Of the which feare and honour, S. <hi>Peter</hi> hath deliuered vnto vs the manifeſt knowledge,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.17.</note> ſaying, As the ſeruants of God, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour all men, loue brotherly fellowſhip, feare God, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King. Thus farre <hi>Fulgent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our countrie man <hi>Beda,</hi> for his great learning called <hi>Venerable,</hi> is of the ſame minde. Dauid (ſaith he) for two cauſes ſpared Saul,<note place="margin">lib. 4. expoſit. in Samuel.</note> who had perſecuted him moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiouſly. Firſt, for that he was his Lord, annointed with holy oile.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And ſecondly, to inſtruct vs by morall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, that we ought not to ſtrike our gouernours,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14168:20"/>
(though they vniuſtly oppreſſe vs) with the ſword of our lips: nor preſume ſlanderouſly, to teare the hemme of their ſuperfluous actions. So farre he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth about the yeare 846. agniſed all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to <hi>Lotharius</hi> the Emperour: I doe profeſſe and promiſe (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>) to obſerue and keepe vnuiolably,<note place="margin">Cap. de capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulis, diſt. 15.</note> as much as lieth in me, for the time preſent and to come, your imperiall ordinances and commandements: toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the decrees of your Biſhops, my predeceſſors: If any man informe your Maieſtie otherwiſe, know cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, that he is a lier. So farrre <hi>Leo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Biſhops of Spaine aſſembled in a nationall councell at <hi>Toledo,</hi> made this decree againſt periurie and treaſon. <hi>Quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> amodo ex nobis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concill. Tol. 5. Canon. 2 circa annum Dom. 636.</note> Whoſoeuer among vs ſhall from this time forward, violate the oath which he hath taken for the ſafegard of this countrie, the ſtate of the Gothiſh nation, &amp; the preſeruation of the Kings Maieſtie: whoſoeuer ſhall attempt the Kings death, or depoſition: whoſoeuer ſhall by tyrannicall preſumption aſpire to the regall throne; let him be accurſed before the holy ſpirit, before the bleſſed Saints, let him be caſt out of the catholique Church, which he hath polluted by periurie, let him haue no communion with Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an men, nor portion with the iuſt, but let him be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the deuill and his angels eternally, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his complices, that they may be tied in the bond of damnation, which were ioyned in the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſedition. Thus farre the fathers in that Synod.</p>
            <p>I conclude therfore with theſe learned Fathers, that it is not for the people, otherwiſe then with humilitie and obedience, to controll the actions of their gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14168:21"/>
but their dutie is onely to call vpon the God of heauen, and ſo ſubmit themſelues to his mercie, by whoſe ordinance the ſcepter is fallen into his hand and power, that enioyeth the crowne, whether he be good or bad. A right of depoſing, muſt be either in him that hath an higher power, which is onely God: or in him, that hath better right to the crowne: which the Pope cannot haue, becauſe he is a ſtraunger: nor the Peeres, or people, becauſe they are ſubiects. Be the king for his religion impious, for his gouernment vniuſt, for his life licentious, the ſubiect muſt endure him, the Biſhop muſt reprooue him, the counſellor muſt aduiſe him, all muſt praie for him, and no mortall man hath authoritie to diſturbe or diſplace him, as may euidently be ſeene by the chapter following.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>The fifth chapter confirmeth this Doctrine by the fathers of the fourth <hi>300</hi> yeares.</head>
            <p>IN this age of the Church, the Popes exalted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues aboue all that is called god, &amp; vpon priuate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſures and quarrels, did curſe and ban Princes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſing their neighbour-nations, and perſwading their owne ſubiects, to make warre againſt them, as if Chriſt had ordeyned his Sacraments, not to be ſeales of grace, and helpes of our faith, but hookes to catch kingdoms, and rods to ſcourge ſuch Potentates as would not, or could not procure the Popes fauour. How farre theſe Popiſh practiſes, did diſpleaſe the godly and learned, I will ſhew by S. <hi>Bernard, Walthramus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nanum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> the epiſtle <hi>Apolegeticall</hi> of the Church of <hi>Leige</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14168:21"/>
againſt <hi>Paſchalis</hi> the Pope, and the author of <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth his life.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> in one of his ſermons vpon the words of <hi>Christ, I am the vine,</hi> commendeth the anſwer of a certaine King, <hi>Bene quidam rex, cum percuſſus humana ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitta, &amp;c.</hi> It was well ſaid of a King when he was ſhot into the bodie with an arrowe, and they that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, deſired him to be bound vntill the arrowes head weare cut out, for that the leaſt motion of his bodie would endanger his life: no (quoth he) it doth not beſeeme a King to be bound, let the kings power be euer ſafe and at libertie. And the ſame father in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Ludovicus Craſſus</hi> the king of France teacheth ſubiects, how to rebell and fight againſt their Princes; <hi>Quicquid vobis de regno veſtro de anima &amp; corona veſtra facere placuerit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Been. epiſt. 221.</note> Whatſoeuer you pleaſe to doe with your kingdome, your ſoule, or your crowne, we that are the children of the Church cannot endure or diſſemble the iniuries, contempt, and conculcation of our mother. Queſtionleſſe we will ſtand and fight euen vnto death in our mothers behalfe, and vſe ſuch weapons, as we may lawfully, I mean not ſwords and ſpeares, but praiers and teares to God.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 7. had depoſed <hi>Henrie</hi> the 4. he gaue away the Empire to one <hi>Rodolphus</hi> duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> that was a ſworne ſubiect to that diſtreſſed Emperour: which <hi>Rodolph,</hi> in a battaile againſt his ſoueraigne Lord, loſt his <hi>right-hand,</hi> and gained a deadly wound. After his death, the Pope made one <hi>Hermanus</hi> king of <hi>Germanie,</hi> who enioyed his kingdome but a little time, for he was ſlaine with a ſtone, which a woman threwe vpon him
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14168:22"/>
from a turret, as he made an aſſault (in ſport) againſt his owne caſtle, to trie the valour of his ſouldiers. Then did <hi>Egbertus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex vita Hen. quarti quae habetur in faſciculo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſcienda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Coloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ae impreſſo.</note> by the Popes encouragement aſcend the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall throne, whereon he ſat but a while: for as he ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped aſide from his armie into a mill, to reſt himſelfe in the heat of the day, he was diſcouered by the miller to the Emperours friends, and loſt his life for his labour. During this hurly-burly in that ſtate, <hi>Walthramus</hi> a godly Biſhop, wrote to one <hi>Ludovicus</hi> an Earle of the Empire, diſwading him from partaking with the ſeditious againſt that good Emperour, whom the Pope had depoſed. <hi>Walthram</hi> by the grace of God, that he is, to <hi>Lewes</hi> the noble Prince, with inſtance of prayer, offreth himſelfe in all things ſeruiceable. Concord is profitable to euery realme, and iuſtice much to be deſired: theſe vertues are the mother of devotion, and the conſecration of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie. But whoſoeuer ſeeketh after ciuill diſſention, and incenſeth other to the effuſion of blood, he is a murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, &amp; partaketh with him, who gaping for blood, goeth about ſeeking who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deuoure: The worthie veſſel of election, that was taken vp to the third heauen, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth, ſaying, Let euerie ſoule ſubmit himſelfe to the higher power, there is no power but from God. He that reſiſteth power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God. If that be true (which ſome men prate among women and the vulgar ſorte) that we ought not to be ſubdued to the kingly power, Then it is falſe which the Apoſtle tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that euery ſoule muſt ſubmit himſelfe vnder pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſuperioritie.<note place="margin">Epiſtol. Wal. quae habetur in appendice Marian Scot.</note> Can the truth lie? did not Chriſt the Lord ſpeake by the Apoſtle? Why doe we prouoke the Lord? are we ſtronger then he? Doth not he thinke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14168:22"/>
ſtronger then the Lord, that reſiſteth the ordinance of God? ſeeing there is no power but of God: what ſaith the Prophet? Confounded be they that ſtriue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, and they that reſiſt him ſhall periſh. <hi>Rodolphus, Hermanus, Egbertus,</hi> with many other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, reſiſted the ordinance of God, in <hi>Henrie</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, but loe they are confounded, as though they had neuer beene, for as their end was ill, their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning could not be good, &amp;c. <hi>Haec ille.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Paſchalis</hi> ſeeing the bad ſucceſſe of thoſe ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſubiects, which his predeceſſors <hi>Gregorie</hi> and <hi>Vrba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> had armed againſt <hi>Henrie,</hi> that worthie Emperour: did perſwade the Emperours owne ſonne, againſt all law of God, nature, and nations, to rebell againſt his Father. The Biſhop of <hi>Leige</hi> tooke the Emperours part, againſt this young Prince, for the which he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, his Church interdicted, and <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of Flaunders commanded by the Pope, as he hoped to haue the forgiuenes of his ſinnes and the fauour of the Church of Rome, to deſtroie that Biſhop and his falſe preiſts.</p>
            <p>The Churchmen of <hi>Leige</hi> terrified with the Popes excommunication, and fearing the Earles oppreſſion, wrote an <hi>apologie</hi> for themſelues about the yeare 1106. We are excommunicate (ſay they) becauſe we obey our Biſhop, who hath taken part with his Lord the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.<note place="margin">Epiſtol. Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dienſium a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Scard.</note> Theſe are the beginnings of ſorrowe: for Sathan beeing looſed, compaſſeth the earth, and hath made a diuiſion betweene the Prince and the Prieſt: who can iuſtly blame the Biſhop that taketh his Lords part, to whom he hath ſworne allegiance? periurie is a great
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14168:23"/>
ſinne, whereof they cannot be ignorant, that by newe ſchiſme and nouell tradition, doe promiſe to abſolue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from the guilt of periurie, that forſweare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to their Lord the King, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the progreſſe of their <hi>apologie</hi> they determine three great queſtions: firſt, whether the Pope hath power to excommunicate Kings? Secondly, to whom it belongeth to inflict temporall puniſhment, when Church-men of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend againſt faith, vnitie, or good manners? And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what remedie ſubiects haue againſt their kings, that are impious or tyrannous? <hi>Si quis reſpectu ſancti ſpiritus, &amp;c.</hi> If any man hauing reſpect to the ſpirit of God, ſhall turne ouer the old &amp; new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he ſhall plainly find that kings, ought not at all or very hardly be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, whether we conſider the etimologie of their names, or the nature of their exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication. Euen till this day hath this point been queſtioned, and neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined. Kings may be admoniſhed and reprooued, by ſuch as be diſcreete and ſober men, for Chriſt the King of Kings in earth, who hath placed them in his owne ſtead, hath reſerued them to his owne iudgement, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Their anſwer to the ſecond queſtion, is grounded on the teſtimonie of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the practiſe of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the authoritie of Paul. Kings (ſay they) and Emperours by their publike lawes, haue forbidden he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, to enioye any worldly poſſeſſion. Wherefore ſeeing we are no heretiques, and that it belongeth not to the Pope, but to kings and Emperours to puniſh he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, why doth our Lord <hi>Paſchalis,</hi> ſend Robert, his armourbearer, to deſtroie the poſſeſſions and to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the villages of the Churches, which in caſe they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14168:23"/>
deſerued deſtruction, ought to be deſtroied by the edict of Kings and Emperours, which carie the ſword not without good cauſe? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For anſwer to the third queſtion, they ſhew by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie places of Scripture, that there is no other helpe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt euill Princes, then prayer and patience. <hi>Nihil mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do pro Imperatore noſtro dicimus, &amp;c.</hi> We will for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſay nothing in defence of our Emperour, but this we ſay, though he were as bad as you report him to be, we would endure his gouernment, becauſe our ſinnes haue deſerued ſuch a gouernor. Be it: we muſt needs graunt againſt our will, that the Emperour is an Arch-heretike, an invader of the kingdome, a worſhipper of the Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naicall Idol, and accurſed by the Apoſtles and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like men, as you ſay of him: euen ſuch a Prince ought not to be reſiſted by violence, but endured by patience and praier. <hi>Moſes</hi> brought many plagues vpon <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whoſe heart God had hardened, but it was by praier and the lifting vp his hands to heauen. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> requireth praiers to be made for all men, for Kings and ſuch as are in authoritie: which kings were neither Catholikes nor Chriſtians. <hi>Baruch</hi> alſo from the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> wrote vnto the Iewes, which were captiues vnto the king of Babylon, that they muſt pray for the life of Nabuchodonoſer the king of Babylon, and Balthazar his ſonne, that their daies in earth may be as the daies of heauen, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Epiſt. 1. eod.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth why we ought to pray for euill kings, namely, that vnder them we may lead a quiet life. It would become an Apoſtolike man, to follow the Apoſtles doctrine: it were propheticall to follow the Prophet, &amp;c. <hi>Thus farre they in their Epiſtle Apologeticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14168:24"/>
               <note place="margin">Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Hen. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>He that wrote the life of this Emperour <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, aniauncient, a modeſt, and an impartiall relator of ſuch occurrents as happened in his time, declareth his diſlike of the Popes practiſes, and the <hi>Germaines</hi> tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults againſt their ſaid ſoueraigne Lord. <hi>Magnum mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do documentum datum eſt:</hi> A great inſtruction was giuen to the world that no man ſhould riſe againſt his maſter. For the hand of <hi>Rodolph</hi> beeing cut off, ſhewed a moſt iuſt puniſhment of periurie; he feared not to violate his fidelitie ſworne to the King, and his right hand was puniſhed, as if other woundes had not beene ſufficient to bring him to his death, that by the plague of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, the fault of rebellion might be perceiued: thus farre he.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>The ſixth Chapter prooveth the ſame by the teſtimonie of the Writers from the <hi>12.</hi> hundred yeares downeward.</head>
            <p>I Will for concluſion produce <hi>Otho Friſingenſis, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aquinas, Gratianus, Philip the faire</hi> king of <hi>France,</hi> the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the 1. <hi>Vincentius,</hi> and <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi> that afterward was Pope, by the name of <hi>Pius Secundus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Otho Friſing. in his epiſtle dedicatorie before his Chronicle.</note>
               <hi>Otho Friſingenſis</hi> hath an excellent ſaying in his epiſtle dedicatorie to <hi>Frederick Barbaroſſa, Cum nulla perſona mundialis inveniatur quae mundi legibus non ſubiaceat, &amp;c.</hi> Although no earthly man can be found, that is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the lawes of the world, and in reſpect of ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, liable to correction: Kings as it were placed ouer lawes, are not reſtrained by them, but reſerued to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14168:24"/>
of God, according to the words of the King and Prophet, <hi>Againſt thee onely haue I ſinned.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note> It becommeth therefore a king, both in reſpect of the noble diſpoſition of his minde, and the ſpirituall illumination of his ſoule, to haue God, the king of kings, and Lord of lords, euer in his minde, and by all meanes poſſible, to take heede, that he fall not into the hands of God, ſeeing it is (as the Apoſtle ſaith) a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God. It is more fearefull for kings, then for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other; becauſe kings haue none but God himſelfe aboue them, whome they neede feare. It ſhall be ſo much more horrible for them, by how much they may offend more freely, then other men. <hi>So farre Otho.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimine prin. lib. 1. c. 6.</note> (if the tractare <hi>de regimene princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum</hi> be his) maketh three ſorts of kings: Kings by <hi>electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Kings by <hi>ſubordination,</hi> and Kings by <hi>ſucceſſion.</hi> For the firſt, he ſaith, that they which did eſtabliſh, may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh: for the ſecond, we muſt haue our recourſe to him that did ſurrogate the ſubordinate King: as the Iewes did to <hi>Caeſar</hi> againſt <hi>Herod:</hi> for the laſt, his reſolution is, <hi>Recurrendum eſſe ad omnium regem deum,</hi> that we muſt flie to God, the King of all kings, in whoſe onely power it is, to mollifie the cruell heart of a tyrant. And that men, may obtaine this at the hands of God, they muſt ceaſe from ſinne; for wicked Princes, by diuine permiſſion are exalted to puniſh the ſinnes of the people, <hi>tollenda est i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pa vt ceſſet tyrannorum plag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> we muſt therefore remooue our ſinnes, that God may take away his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: Thus farre <hi>Thomas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gratianus,</hi> which compiled the decrees, is verie pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorie, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ought not to medle
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14168:25"/>
with the temporall ſword, the ſtate of common wealthes, or the change of Princes. He ſaith nothing indeede <hi>de Regni ordinibus,</hi> which in his time, and a 100. yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, neuer dreamed of any ſuch authoritie. <hi>Cum Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus qui primus apoſtolorum à domino fuerat electus, materia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem gladium exerceret:</hi> When Peter whom the Lord had firſt choſen of all the Apoſtles, drewe the materiall ſword, to defend his Maſter from the iniuries of the Iewes, he was commanded to ſheath his ſword: <hi>for all that take the ſword,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 26.52.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall periſh by the ſword.</hi> As if Chriſt ſhould haue ſaid, Hitherto it was lawfull for thee and thine aunceſtors to perſecute Gods enemies with the temporall ſword, hereafter thou muſt put vp that ſword into his place,<note place="margin">Cauſ. 23. queſt. 8. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag. 1.</note> and drawe the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God, to ſlay the old man: who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beſide the Prince, and without his authoritie, that hath lawfull power, and as the Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>beareth not the ſword in vaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> to whom euerie ſoule muſt be ſubiect, whoſoeuer (I ſay) without or beſide the Princes authoritie, beareth the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword: Thus farre <hi>Gratian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the yeare a 1300. began a quarrell betweene <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. and <hi>Philippus Pulcher</hi> the French king, about the collation of benefices, prebends, and other eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall promotions. Whereupon the Pope wrote vnto the ſaid king, as followeth: <hi>Boniface</hi> Biſhop, the ſeruant of Gods ſeruants, to his wel-beloued ſonne <hi>Philip,</hi> by Gods grace king of France, Greeting and bleſſing Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall. Feare God and keepe his lawe: We giue thee to vnderſtand that thou art ſubiect to vs both in ſpirituall things, and temporall, and that no gift of benefices or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14168:25"/>
prebends belongeth to thee. If thou haue in thy hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vacant, keepe the profits of them to the ſucceſſors, and if thou haſt beſtowed any, we decree the collation voide, and recall it, how farre ſoeuer it hath proceeded. Whoſoeuer beleeueth otherwiſe, we account him a foole: Dated at <hi>Lateran</hi> the fourth of the Calends of December, and in the 6. yeare of our Papacie. King <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> returned his haughtineſſe, a correſpondent anſwear, <hi>viz. Philip</hi> by the grace of God, King of Fraunce, to <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface</hi> bearing himſelfe for Pope,<note place="margin">Philip. Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</note> 
               <hi>Salutem modicam ſiue nulla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Sciat tua maxima fatuitas.</hi> Little health or none at all. Let thy great fooleſhip know, that in temporall things we are ſubiect to no man. And that the gifts of prebends and eccleſiaſticall promotions, made and to be made by vs, were and ſhall be lawfull, both in time paſt and in time to come. For ſuch collations belong to vs in the right of our crowne: wherefore, we will manfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the poſſeſſours of the ſaid dignities, and doe iudge them that thinke otherwiſe fooles and madmen. Giuen at Paris the wedneſday after Candlemaſſe, 1301. Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe this King that did ſo ſcornefully reiect the Popes chalenge pretended from Chriſt, would little regard the claime of the Nobles, deriued but from the people.</p>
            <p>The ſame buſie <hi>Boniface,</hi> of whom ſome write, that he came in like a <hi>fox</hi> craftely, raigned like a <hi>lyon</hi> cruelly, and died like a <hi>dogge</hi> miſerably, would take vpon him the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of a controverſie between the Kings of <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland,</hi> and commanded King <hi>Edward</hi> of <hi>England</hi> either to ceaſe his claime, or to ſend his procurators to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike ſea, to ſhewe his right, and to receiue ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the Pope, as iuſtice and equitie would require.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14168:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The Lords and commons then aſſembled in Parliament at <hi>Lincolne</hi> ſent <hi>Boniface</hi> this anſwear in the kings behalfe. Whereas our moſt dread Lord <hi>Edward</hi> by the grace of God, the Noble King of <hi>England,</hi> cauſed your letters to be read openly before vs, touching certaine occurrents of ſtate betweene him and the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> we did not a little marvaile at the contents thereof, ſo ſtrange and wonderfull, as the like hath neuer beene heard of. We knowe (moſt holy father) and it is well knowne in this realme, and alſo to other nations, that the King of <hi>England</hi> ought not to make anſwer for his right before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny iudge eccleſiaſticall or ſecular: by reaſon of the free eſtate of his royall dignitie and cuſtome,<note place="margin">Parliament at Lincolne quoted by M. Beken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw.</note> without breach at all times vnviolably obſerued: Wherefore after trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie had and diligent deliberation, this was our reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that our ſaid king ought not to anſwer in iudgement, nor ſend procurators or meſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers to your court: ſeeing that tendeth manifeſtly to the diſinheriting of the right of the crowne, the ouerthrowe of the ſtate of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the breach of the liberties, cuſtomes, and lawes of our fathers, for the keeping whereof, we are bound by the dutie of an oath, and will (by Gods helpe) maintaine and defend with all our power and ſtrength, &amp;c. Dated at <hi>Lincolne Ann. Dom.</hi> 1301. <hi>&amp; anno Edvardi primi</hi> 29. This was then the reſolution of the ſtate of this land: if our late ſectaries <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Puritan,</hi> bring in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doctrine, we may not leaue the cawſey of truth &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, whereon our forefathers walked to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, to followe theſe newe guides, in their by-paths of pride, diſobedience, and contempt of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to our deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:14168:26"/>
               <hi>Vincentius</hi> in his <hi>Speculo Historiali</hi> hath a notable place to diſſwade from ſedition and periurie.<note place="margin">lib. 15. cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Vt pace omnium bonorum dixerim, haec ſola nouitas (ne dicam haereſis) nec dum è mundo emerſerat.</hi> That I may ſpeake with the fauour of all good men, this meere noueltie (if not hereſie) was not ſprung vp in the world, that preiſts ſhould teach ſubiects, that they owe no ſubiection to wicked kings, and albeit they haue giuen an oath of fidelitie vnto them, they are not bound to keepe it: Nay they that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey an euill Prince, are to be held as excommunicated, and all ſuch as rebell againſt him, are free from the guilt of the crime of periurie. So farre he.</p>
            <p>I will end this chapter with <hi>Aeneas Siluius,</hi> who died in the yeare 1464. <hi>Sit tandem finis litium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pius 2. de or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu &amp; author. imperij cap. 23.</note> Let there be an end of contention, and one principall head to determine all temporall matters; let the occaſion of perpetuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate be taken away, let men acknowledge themſelues ſubiect to their Prince, &amp; giue reuerence to him, whom God hath made his vicegerent on earth. As that which God commandeth muſt be obeyed without contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, ſo the temporall commandements of Caeſar, may not be reſiſted. But let the Kings themſelues beware that they oppreſſe no man vniuſtly, nor giue their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cauſe to crie to God againſt them, for the earth is the Lords and the fulneſſe thereof: he will not forget the crie of the poore: and for the ſinne of the Prince he tranſlateth the gouernment from one nation to another. There is nothing more offenſiue to the greateſt God the king and creator of heauen and earth, then the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of iuſtice, and the oppreſſion of the poore: as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, The poore ſhall not alway be forgotten,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14168:27"/>
and the patient abiding of the needie ſhall not periſh for euer. So farre <hi>Siluius.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>The ſeauenth Chapter ſheweth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of Papiſt and Puritan for the depoſition of Kings, and their diſcord about the meanes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be imployed in the execution of their deſignements.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CHilderick</hi> was depoſed, and <hi>Pipine</hi> crowned King of France about the yeare 750. The truth of which hiſtorie is this. <hi>Childericke</hi> voide of all princely grauitie, gaue himſelfe ouer to pleaſure and wantonneſſe, leauing the burthen of the ſtate to <hi>Pipinus,</hi> that was his Lord <hi>Marſhall:</hi> Who conſpired with the Nobles, to aduance himſelfe, by the depoſition of the king his maſter. To ſet a better colour on the matter, <hi>Pipine</hi> ſent his Chaplaine to Pope <hi>Zacharie,</hi> to haue his anſwer to this Queſtion: <hi>Whether ſhould be King, he that bare the name and did nothing, or he that gouerned the kingdome?</hi> The Pope gaue ſentence with the Marſhall againſt the King, whereupon, <hi>Childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> was made a ſhorne Monke, and <hi>Pipine</hi> a crowned king.</p>
            <p>It is a wonder to ſee how theſe oppoſite ſectaries, do inſiſt vpon this fact of the Frenchmen, to iuſtifie their dangerous doctrine, and ſeditious conſpiracies againſt Princes. As Card. <hi>Bellarmine de pontif. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>Thomas Harding</hi> againſt the <hi>Apologie</hi> of the Church of England <hi>fol.</hi> 181. Franc. <hi>Feuardentius</hi> in his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries on <hi>Heſter</hi> pag. 85. <hi>Boucher alias: Raynolds de iuſta ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatione Henrici.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Ficklerus de iure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratuum
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14168:27"/>
fol.</hi> 30. <hi>Alexander Carerius patauinus de poteſtate papae lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>D. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rta de temporali &amp; ſpirituali ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficis poteſtate lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 23: and <hi>Doleman in his conference tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſucceſſion parte.</hi> 1. cap. 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 48. And alſo theſe <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, Chriſtopher Goodman in his treatiſe of obedience pag.</hi> 53. <hi>George Buchanan de iure Regni apud Scotos p.</hi> 47. <hi>Danaeus de politia Chriſtiana lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 221. <hi>Brutus Celta de iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re magiſtratuum pag.</hi> 286. <hi>Phyladelphus dialogo</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 65. <hi>Franc. Hottomanus</hi> in his <hi>Francogallia cap.</hi> 12. and <hi>Speculum tyrannidis Philipi Regis pag.</hi> 27. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> which aſcribe this depoſing power to the pope, endeauour by tooth and naile, to diſprooue that intereſt which the <hi>Puritans</hi> grant the peeres or the people. Firſt, this example ſerued <hi>Gregorie</hi> 7. to excuſe his preſumptuous practiſes againſt <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth. <hi>Quidum Ramanus pontifex.</hi> A certaine Biſhop of Rome depoſed a king of France,<note place="margin">lib de vrit. Eccleſ. apud Scard. pag. 3.</note> not ſo much for his ill life, as for that he was not fit for gouerment, and placed <hi>Pipine,</hi> which was father to <hi>Charles</hi> the great, in his place: abſoluing all the Frenchmen from the oath of allegeance, which they had ſworne to their king. Thus farre <hi>Gregorie</hi> in an epiſtle to one <hi>Herimanus,</hi> that was Biſhop of Metz in France.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Harding</hi> concludeth from this fact, a diuine power in the pope.<note place="margin">Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. of the Apol <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. fol. 181.</note> Can you not ſee (ſaith <hi>Harding</hi>) what ſtrength and power is in the pope, which is able with a word, to place and diſplace the mightieſt King in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope? with a word, I ſay, for I am ſure you can ſhewe vs of no armie, that he ſent to execute his will. Is it in the power of a man (thinke you) to appoint kingdomes? can the Deuill himſelfe, at his pleaſure ſet vp and depoſe Kings? no ſurely. Much leſſe can any member of his do
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14168:28"/>
the ſame. Remember you what Chriſt ſaid, when the Iewes obiected, that he did caſt out deuils in the name of the prince of deuils? beware you ſinne not againſt the holy Ghoſt, who confeſſe that the Pope hath pulled downe and ſet vp Kings. Which thing vndoubtedly he could neuer do profitably and peaceably, but by the great power of God, &amp;c. So farre <hi>Harding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">De Pontif. lib. 2. cap. 17.</note>Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the grand-maſter of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, cannot indure to heare that this depoſition was done by any other then the papall authoritie. The Pope (ſaith he) <hi>Iudicauit licere Frauncis, regnum Childerici in Pipinum transferre.</hi> The Pope gaue iudgement that the Frenchmen might lawfully transfer <hi>Childericks</hi> kingdome to <hi>Pipin:</hi> and did abſolue them from the oath which they had ſworne vnto him. No man that hath his right wit can denie this to be lawfull. For the very euent hath prooued, that change to be moſt fortunate: ſeeing the kingdome of Fraunce, was neuer more potent, nor religion more flouriſhing, then vnder <hi>Pipin</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> his ſonne. Thus farre <hi>Bellarm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Cardinals reaſon from the ſucceſſe to the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the fact, will conclude well for the Turke, who hath longer continued, more flouriſhed and inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his ſtate, then the houſe of <hi>Pipin.</hi> Heare in a word the true ſucces of <hi>Pipins</hi> poſteritie out of <hi>Benuentus Imo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſis</hi> and <hi>Paulus Aemilius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Benventus Imolenſis.</note> The firſt of that line was <hi>Charles</hi> the great, in whoſe time the Empire was diuided. The ſecond was <hi>Ludouicus Pius,</hi> againſt whome <hi>Lotha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> an vnnaturall ſonne, did conſpire: who thruſt his father to a cloiſter, and placed himſelfe in the throne, where he ſate like a tyrant, till he was alſo depoſed. The
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14168:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
fourth was <hi>Ludovicus</hi> 2. a man vnfortunate in all his doings. The fifth was <hi>Ludovicus</hi> 3. whome they call <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovicus nihili,</hi> or <hi>Lewes</hi> no-bodie. The 6.<note place="margin">Paulus Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius.</note> was Charles the <hi>bald,</hi> a very coward. The 7. was <hi>Charolus Craſſus,</hi> as very foole. <hi>Arnulphus</hi> the eight of that progenie, was eaten with lice. The 9. was <hi>Ludovicus</hi> 4. in whome that race en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander Carerius</hi> inferreth the abſolute ſoueraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the <hi>Pope</hi> ouer all Kings, euen to depoſe them, and to tranſpoſe the Realmes, from the inſufficiencie of the Nobles and people. <hi>Esto quod verùm ſit Papam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">de poteſtate Pontif. l. 2. cap. 3. num 6.</note> 
               <hi>non depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſſe regem Francia:</hi> Be it true that the Pope did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the king of France, but gaue conſent to the Peeres and people to depoſe him, this is a moſt manifeſt proofe of our intent: that kings haue one, if not many ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, <hi>viz.</hi> the Barons and people of their kingdome: and ouerthroweth their poſition and concluſion, <hi>That Kings haue in temporall things no ſuperiour,</hi> no, not the Biſhop of Rome. But ſeeing the Barons &amp; people, could neither iudge nor depriue him, becauſe they wanted coactiue power, which Vaſſalls or ſubiects haue not ouer their ſoueraigne, it followeth neceſſarily, that the Pope by his princely power, as ſuperior to the King in temporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, might lawfully depoſe him. Thus farre <hi>Carerius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D. Marta,</hi> is as peremptorie for the Pope, againſt the pretended claime of the Peeres or the people. <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericus priuatus eſt regno Franciae obſtupiditatem &amp; inepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem in adminiſtrando:</hi> Childerick was depriued of the kingdome of France, for his ſtupiditie and vnfitneſſe to gouerne. They that ſay he was not depriued by the Pope alone, but by them that deſired another king, doe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14168:29"/>
not anſwer the reaſons alleadged for the Popes ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power in temporalties: nay they confirme the Popes power. <hi>Baldus</hi> asketh this queſtion, when the Emperour is vnprofitable, or madde, or a drunkard, may the people depoſe him, or aſſigne him a coadiutor? No, ſaith he,<note place="margin">de temp. &amp; ſpir. Pontif. poteſt. part. 1. cap. 23. nu. 15, 16, 17.</note> the Pope muſt doe it, <hi>for the Pope is the crowne and braine of the people.</hi> And we haue prooued before, that God did giue no iuriſdiction to the people, but to <hi>Moſes</hi> and his ſucceſſors. Wherefore the vaſſals or Peeres which repreſent the people, haue no power com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the Pope, in the depoſing of Princes. And in that they ſay, that the Frenchmen deſired another king, it is a great confirmation, that the Pope hath right to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of kingdomes. He vſeth to deſire, who hath not of his owne: or cannot of himſelfe effect that, which he would haue done: Thus farre <hi>Marta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that plead for the ſtate of the <hi>Laitie,</hi> are as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident againſt the Pope and clergie. <hi>Vt paucis dicam</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iunius) hoc fecit Zacharias vt dominus aut vt mandatarius, authoritate, inſtructus à domino,</hi> that I may vſe ſewe words, the Pope depoſed <hi>Childericke</hi> either as his Lord, or as a mandatarie hauing authoritie from the Lord; but he did it neither way. Not as Lord, how could he be Lord in France, that in thoſe dayes had no Lordſhip in Rome? he did it not as mandatarie, for then he ought to haue ſhewed his authoritie, which he neither did, nor could ſhewe. Chriſt would not diuide a priuate inheritance, ſhall <hi>Zacharie</hi> then preſume to depoſe kings or tranſpoſe kingdomes? Thus farre <hi>Iunius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeterum quod monachus iſte</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lambertus Danaeus</hi>) whereas this monke <hi>Bellarmine</hi> contendeth, that <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericke</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:14168:29"/>
was lawfully depoſed by Pope <hi>Zacharias,</hi> a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, a Prieſt, no Magiſtrate, but (in this reſpect) a priuate perſon, though he were Biſhop of Rome.<note place="margin">Reſp. Dana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad Bellar. l. 2. c. 17. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>16.</note> Will he euer be able to prooue or defend his aſſertion? Can <hi>Zacharie</hi> haue authorie in <hi>France,</hi> being a ſtranger? can he depoſe the publike Magiſtrate, beeing but a priuate perſon? or transferre that principality to <hi>Pipin</hi> that he hath no right vnto? and commit ſo many ſacriledges and impieties, ſtealing from <hi>Childericke,</hi> and giuing to <hi>Pipin</hi> another mans right? authoriſing ſubiects to violate their oaths, which they had ſworne to their king? tranſpoſing king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes from one man to another, whereas it doth onely belong to God to depoſe kings, and diſpoſe of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes? thou maiſt ſee <hi>(Bellarmine)</hi> how many outrages this thy <hi>Zacharie</hi> hath committed, beſide that he did thruſt his ſickle into an other mans harueſt, and medled with the cobler beyond his laſt, in that, beeing but a Prieſt he tooke vpon him the deciſion of the right of kingdomes. Thus farre <hi>Danaeus,</hi> who is not ſo violent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope, as he is virulent for the depoſing power of Peeres, or ſtates of the kingdome.<note place="margin">Danaeus pol. Chriſtian. l. 6. c. 3. pag. 414.</note> The kings (ſaith he) of Lacedemonia had the <hi>Ephori</hi> to controll them. The ſtates-men of the Romane common-wealth, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Emperours, which were tyrants, and abuſed their authoritie. The French-ſtate hath often dethroned their kings: The Nobles of Spaine may doe it by their law: And the hiſtorie of the Scottiſh affaires (excellently well written by<note n="*" place="margin">mulus mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſcabit.</note> 
               <hi>Buchanan</hi>) doth report that the ſtates-men of that countrie, haue many times depriued the kings of Scotland. Finally, naturall reaſon, and the practiſe of all nations doth confirme, that the ſtates-men in euery
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14168:30"/>
kingdome, may depoſe kings, that are peccant. So farre he.<note place="margin">cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Hottoman</hi> in his <hi>Franco Gallia,</hi> hath a long chapter to prooue that this might be done lawfully, by the Peeres, or the people, but in no caſe by the Pope or the clergie.</p>
            <p>Men cannot ſaie (as it is in the prouerbe) <hi>nimium al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cando veritas amittitur,</hi> ſeeing that in this oppoſition, the truth is not loſt, but diuided among them. For their premiſſes, brought together, wil vnauoidably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that this depoſing power, is neither in the Pope, the Peeres, nor the people. Though it were, the reaſon of the ſeditious <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritans, à facto adius,</hi> is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſticall in the ſchooles, where nothing can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded <hi>ex meris particularibus,</hi> of meere particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. Abſurd in law, <hi>quia legibus non exemplis vivitur,</hi> for men muſt doe as the law requireth, not as other men practiſe. Erroneous in diuinitie, <hi>non ideo quia factum cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Conſen. de mendacio cap. 9.</note> 
               <hi>faciendum credamus, ne violemus praeceptum dum ſectamur exemplum:</hi> We may not doe that, which hath beene done by other men, leaſt we breake the law of of God, in following the example of man. And dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in policie, as my <hi>Lord of Northampton,</hi> the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of learning, obſerueth. <q>The flie (ſaith that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Earle) ſitting on the cart wheele, might as well wonder at the duſt raiſed in the way, as <hi>Gregorie</hi> or <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie,</hi> draw counſell to power, and make that fact their owne, which was hammered in the forge of ambition, countenanced with the colour of neceſſitie, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by <hi>Pipin,</hi> a miniſter, that beeing wearie of ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, reſolued by this tricke, when the meanes were fitted and prepared to the plot, to make himſelfe abſolute. The caſe of Kings were pitifull, if <hi>ex factis ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularibus,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:14168:30"/>
it were lawfull to drawe leaden rules in their diſgrace.</q> Thus farre the Earle.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>The eight Chapter ſheweth the danger of this Doctrine, and the originall of the Puritan poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, concerning the power of ſtaſteſmen to puniſh and depoſe Princes in Monarchies.</head>
            <p>THeſe deſperate attempts, ſuggeſted by the Deuill, executed by the people, encouraged by the ſtate, &amp; approoued by the Pope, muſt ſerue as admonitions to Princes, to humble themſelues before God: <hi>Qui non dabit ſanctos ſuos in captionem dentibus eorum,</hi> who will not giue his Saints for a pray to their teeth. For it is not heard (as our great King remembreth) <hi>That any Prince forgeteth himſelfe in his dutie to God, or in his vocation?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Law of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. p. 60.</note> 
               <hi>But God with the greatneſſe of the plague reuengeth the greatneſſe of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe practiſes therefore muſt be no preſident for Peeres, or people to follow, becauſe God hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Chriſtian ſubiects to reſiſt, though kings raigne as Tyrants; &amp; commanded them to endure with patience, though they ſuffer as Innocents. And alſo, becauſe that in ſtead of releeuing the Common-wealth out of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, which is euer the pretence of ſeditions practiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, they ſhall heape miſcheefe on it, and deſolation on themſelues: as <hi>(Aquinas)</hi> if he be the author of the booke <hi>de regim. principum,</hi> ſheweth manifeſtly. <hi>Eſſet multitudini periculoſum &amp; eius rectoribus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">de regim. princ. l. 1. c. 6.</note> It were dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſubiects and gouernours, that any ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14168:31"/>
to take away the life of princes, though they were tyrants: for commonly, not the well diſpoſed, but the ill affected men, doe thruſt themſelues into that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And the gouerment of good Kings, is as odious to bad men, as the rule of tyrants to good people. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the kingdome, by this preſumption would be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in daunger to forgoe a good prince, then a wicked tyrant. So farre <hi>Thomas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that are the authors or abettors of ſedition, can neither avoide ſhame in earth, nor eſcape eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Though God the great Iudge do ſometime per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit rebells, in his Iuſtice to preuaile againſt Kings, for their contempt of the lawe of the higheſt, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of their owne dutie. The reward of rebellion ſhall be no better then the recompence of Sathan, who is the inſtrument of the Lords wrath for the puniſhment of all diſobedience. It is moſt true that as ſicke men, neere their death,<note place="margin">Chryſoſtom.</note> haue many idle fancies, ſo the world before the ende thereof ſhall be troubled with many errors. In theſe declining dayes of the world, many countreys, Cities, and Cantons, renounced their old gouernment, and ſubmitted themſelues to ſuch a newe regiment as they beſt liked: for confirmation of which practiſes, there wanted not politike Diuines, (what wine is ſo ſoure that ſome hedge grapes will not yeeld) to inueſt the people and Nobles with the power ouer Kings, to diſpoſe of their kingdomes. The heathen <hi>Politicians</hi> from whome this politike Diuinitie is deriued, knowing not the true God, and hauing no rule to direct them, but naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, thought him no murtherer, but <hi>a defender of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey that killed tyrants.</hi> But this pagan principle, beeing a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14168:31"/>
plant, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath not planted, muſt be plucked vp by the rootes. I can finde no ground of this leud lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, beyond 220. yeares in the Chriſtian world: the firſt authors of it beeing <hi>Iohannes de Pariſiis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. de Parie de poteſt. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia &amp; papali cap. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Iacobus Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> and <hi>Marſilius Patavinus: Vbi peccat rex in temporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iohannes de pariſiis, papa non habet ipſum corrige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re:</hi> when the king offendeth in the temporall gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Pope hath no authoritie to correct him, but the Barons or Peeres of the Realme, and if they either cannot, or dare not meddle with him, they may craue the the Churches aide to ſuppreſſe him: ſo farre <hi>Iohn of Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tota communitas</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iacob Almain) poteſtatem habet principem deponere.</hi> All the communalty,<note place="margin">Iacob Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. eccleſ. cap. 1.</note> hath power to depoſe their Prince, which power the communalty of France vſed, when they depriued their king, not ſo much for his impietie, as for his diſabilitie to manage ſo great a charge: ſo farre <hi>Almain. Regis depoſitio &amp; alterius inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutio</hi> (ſaith <hi>Marſilius Patavinus</hi>) the depoſition of a king,<note place="margin">Marſil. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tav. de tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlat. imperij cap. 6.</note> and the inſtitution of another in his place, belongeth not to the Biſhop of Rome, to any prieſt, or to the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of prieſts, but to the vniuerſall multitude of the ſubiects. So farre he.</p>
            <p>From theſe, the <hi>Puritans</hi> haue learned their error, of the <hi>power of States-men ouer Kings,</hi> then which, no opinion can be more daungerous: where the Nobilitie are as readie to practiſe, as the <hi>Puritan</hi> preachers are to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe. What preſumption is it in men, to paſſe the bounds which God hath ſet them, to controll the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Lord, and his vnſpeakable goodnes, when he maketh triall of the patience of his Saints, by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and tyrannie of cruell kings, that they which are
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14168:32"/>
found patient in trouble, conſtant in truth, and loyall in ſubiection, may be crowned with glorie. Were we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that the <hi>hearts of Kings are in Gods hand,</hi> that the haires of our head are numbred, and that no affliction can befall vs, which God doth not diſpoſe to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our faith, the triall of our conſtancie, or the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of our ſinne, we would as well admire the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God, in permitting tyrants, that our ſinnes may be iudged, and puniſhed in this world, as praiſe his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and fauour, in giuing reſt to his ſeruants, vnder the protection of godly and gracious princes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>The ninth Chapter ſheweth the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall conſent of the Moderne Puritans touching the coercion, depoſition, and killing of Kings whome they call tyrants.</head>
            <p>THe Citizens of <hi>Geneua,</hi> changed the gouerment from a <hi>Monarchie</hi> to a <hi>Democratie</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt, 1536. In the which yeare, <hi>Iohn Calvin</hi> came into that Citie, to viſit his freind <hi>Farellus;</hi> And was choſen the publike reader of diuinitie. At his firſt comming thither, he publiſhed his <hi>Theologicall inſtitutions.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he doth verie learnedly, and Chriſtianly intreat of the authoritie of princes, and the dutie of ſubiects. One onely place is harſhe, and dangerous: deliuered in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and doubtfull tearmes, to excuſe (as I conceiue) the outrage of the Citizens, againſt their prince, whom they had not many weekes before expelled: not to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſe other men to attempt the like againſt their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Magiſtrates. His words are theſe, <hi>Si qui ſunt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14168:32"/>
populares Magiſtratus, ad moderandam regnum libidinem conſttuti.</hi> If there be any popular Magiſtrates, to reſtraine the licentiouſneſſe of Kings, of which kinde were the Ephori oppoſed againſt the Lacedemonian Kings,<note place="margin">Iuſtit. l. 4. 6. 20. ſect. 31.</note> the Tribunes of the people, which curbed the Romane Conſuls, and the Demarchie which brideled the Senate of Athens; And ſuch peraduenture as things now ſtand are the three ſtates in euery kingdome, aſſembled in Parliament. I doe not denie, but theſe in regard of their dutie, ſtand bound to repreſſe the vnrulineſſe of licentious kings: Nay, I affirme, that if they doe but winke at at thoſe kings, which peeuiſhly make hauock of their people, and inſult againſt their communaltie, that they want not the guilt of hainous treacherie, becauſe they betray the libertie of the people, whoſe guardians they know themſelues to be appointed. Thus farre <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</hi> Since which time all <hi>Puritans</hi> haue turned his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction <hi>conditionall,</hi> into an <hi>illative,</hi> his aduerb of <hi>doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> to an <hi>affirmative,</hi> and his permiſſive, <hi>non veto,</hi> into a verb of the <hi>imparative moode,</hi> in their books of regiment ſecular, and diſcipline Eccleſiaſticall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtopher Goodman,</hi> publiſhed a treatiſe of obedience at <hi>Geneva,</hi> not without the verie good liking and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the beſt learned in that citie, 1557.<note place="margin">pag. 119.</note> wherein he affirmeth, That if Magiſtrates tranſgreſſe Gods lawe themſelues, and command others to doe the like, they looſe that honour, and obedience which otherwiſe is due vnto them: and ought no more to be taken for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates: but to be examined and puniſhed as priuate tranſgreſſors: ſo farre <hi>Goodman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much about the ſame time was <hi>Knoxe</hi> his <hi>appellation</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:14168:33"/>
printed in the ſame place,<note place="margin">Geneva, fol. 56.</note> wherein he feareth not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, That it had beene the dutie of the Nobilitie, Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Rulers, and people of England not onely to haue reſiſted <hi>Marie,</hi> that <hi>Iezabel</hi> whom they call their <hi>Queene,</hi> but alſo to haue puniſhed her to the death, with all ſuch as ſhould haue aſſiſted her, what time that ſhe ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſuppreſſe Chriſts Goſpel, to ſhed the blood of the Saints, and to erect that moſt deuilliſh Idolatrie, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall abhominations, and his vſurped tyrannie. Thus farre <hi>Knox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ann.</hi> 1560. <hi>Theodore Beza</hi> printed his <hi>Confeſſions,</hi> wherein he auoucheth, That there are vices inherent in the perſons of Princes, though they be lawfully eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,<note place="margin">pag. 216.</note> by ſucceſſion, or election, <hi>viz.</hi> Vngodlineſſe, couetouſneſſe, ambition, crueltie, luxurie, lecherie, and ſuch like ſinnes which tyrants delight in. What ſhall be done in this caſe to theſe Princes I anſwer (ſaith he) that it belongeth to the ſuperiour powers, ſuch as are the 7. electors in the Empire, and the ſtateſmen of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome almoſt in euerie Monarchie, to reſtraine the fury of tyrants, which if they doe not, they are traytors to their countryes, and ſhall before the Lord giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their treacherie. Thus farre <hi>Beza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1561. The verie yeare after there was a contention betweene the Nobilitie and Clergie of Scotland about this matter,<note place="margin">Renum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cot. l. 17. p. 590.</note> (as <hi>Buchanan</hi> reporteth:) let him tel his owne tale. <hi>Calendis Novembribus regina ad Miſſam:</hi> The Queene vpon the feaſt of All-Saints, added to her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Maſſe all the ſolemnities and ſuperſtitious cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Papiſts; The Miniſters of the Goſpel tooke it verie ill, complained thereof to the people, in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14168:33"/>
their publike congregations, and admoniſhed the nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of their dutie in that behalfe: whereupon roſe a controverſie in a houſe of private meeting, between the Nobles and Preachers, whether the Nobles may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine Idolatrie, that is like to breake out to a generall deſtruction: and by rigor of law, compell the cheefe Magiſtrate to his dutie, when he exceedeth his bounds? The Miniſters of the Church ſtood ſtedfaſt in opinion, as they had formerly done, that the cheefe Magiſtrate may be compelled euen by forcible meanes to liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to law: but the Noble men becauſe of the <hi>Queenes</hi> fauour, hope of honour, or loue of lucre,<note place="margin">Note how baſely the Puritans e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the Nobilitie when they thwart them.</note> did a litle wauer, and thought otherwiſe then the Miniſters: and ſo in the end iudgement paſſed with the Nobles, becauſe they were more in number and of better eſteeme and reputation. Thus farre <hi>Buchanan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1568. The outlandiſh Churches in London conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this Canon in a claſſicall Synode,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ezae epiſt. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Si quiſquam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnantibus legibus patriae:</hi> If any man vſurpe Lordſhip, or Magiſtracie, againſt the lawes and priuiledges of the countrie, or if he that is a lawfull Magiſtrate, doe vniuſtly bereaue his ſubiects of the priuiledges, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties which he hath ſworne to performe vnto them, or oppreſſe them by manifeſt tyrannie, the inferiour officers muſt oppoſe themſelues againſt him, for they are in dutie bound before God, to defend their people, as well from a domeſticall, as a forraigne tyrant. Thus farre they.</p>
            <p>1574. We had ſwarmes of caterpillers: namely,<note place="margin">fol. 145.</note>
               <hi>Diſciplina Eccleſiaſtica</hi> from Rochel, to teach vs, that the ſenate Eccleſiaſticall hath the cheefe moderation of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14168:34"/>
Chriſtian ſocietie, and ought to prouide that no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate be defectiue in his charge, and by common care, counſell, and authoritie to ouerſee, that euerie go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour our cary himſelfe faithfully in his Magiſtracie. Thus farre that author.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">pag. 48.</note>
               <hi>Franco-Gallia</hi> from <hi>Colen,</hi> wherein we finde that the people hath power to dethrone their Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">pag. 300.</note>
               <hi>Iunius de iure Magiſtratuum</hi> (as ſome thinke from <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva,</hi>) wherein it is ſaid, that the people haue the ſame right to depoſe kings that are tyrants, which a generall counſell hath to diſplace a Pope that is an heretique.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius Phyladelphus</hi> from <hi>Edenbruge,</hi> wherein we read,<note place="margin">dialogo. 2. pag. 57.</note> that it was as lawfull for his brethren of France, to defend themſelues againſt the tyrannie of <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, King of that name in France, as for wayfairing men to reſiſt and repell theeues, cutthroats, and wolues: nay further, I am (ſaith he) of opinion with the old peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Rome, that of all good actions the murther of a tyrant is moſt commendable. Thus farre he.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">pag. 206.</note>1577. came forth the <hi>Vindicia contra Tyrannos,</hi> with this reſolution, That Princes are choſen by God, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the people: euery priuate man is ſubiect to the Prince: the Multitude and the officers of ſtate which repreſent the Multitude, are ſuperiours to the Prince: yea they may iudge his actions, and if he make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, puniſh him by forcible meanes. So farre he.</p>
            <p>1584. <hi>Danaeus</hi> finiſhed his booke of Chriſtian policie, wherein among many other he propoundeth, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth a <hi>Noble queſtion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">lib. 3. c. 6.</note> as he termeth it. <hi>Nobilis quaeſtio ſequitur.</hi> A noble queſtion followeth, whether it be lawful for ſubiects to change and alter their gouerment?
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14168:34"/>
Yea whether it may be done by godly men with a good conſcience? his anſwer is. The cheefe Magiſtrate, that notoriouſly and willfully violateth the fundamentall lawes of the kingdome, may be diſplaced by godly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, with a good conſcience. And this is his reaſon, <hi>Reges ſummi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Magiſtratus,</hi> Kings and cheefe Magiſtrates are the vaſſalls of the kingdome, and of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth where they rule: Wherefore, they may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed &amp; deiected when they ſhall obſtinatly attempt any thing, againſt the feudall lawes of the kingdome where they gouerne, as Kings and cheefe Magiſtrates. And it is truly ſaid, that as a generall councell, is aboue the Pope, ſo the kingdome or the Peeres of the Land, are aboue the King. Thus farre <hi>Danaeus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1585.<note place="margin">de iure Reg. pag. 31.</note> 
               <hi>George Buchanan</hi> proclaimed rewards aſwell for murthering kings as killing tygres. If I (ſaith he) had power to make a law, I would command tyrants to be tranſported from the ſocietie of men into ſome ſolitarie place, or els to be drowned in the bottome of the ſea, that the euill ſauour of dead tyrants ſhould not annoy liuing men. Furthermore I would award recompence to be giuen for the ſlaughter of tyrants, not onely of all in generall, but of euery one in particular, as men vſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them for their paines which kill wolues or beares, and deſtroy their young ones. <hi>haec ille.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame yeare <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> commended <hi>Dud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley Fenners</hi> his <hi>Sacra Theologia</hi> (as they call his booke) to the world, wherein men are warranted by ſundry texts of Scripture, moſt miſerably abuſed, to deſtroy tyrants. Therein he (following the common opinion of the <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi>) maketh two ſorts of tyrants, <hi>Tyrannus ſine titulo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">lib. 5. cap. 13. pag. 185.</note>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:14168:35"/>
and <hi>Tyrannus exercitio.</hi> For the tyrant without title: He is confident, that any man may cut his throat. <hi>Huic quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> priuatus reſiſtet, etiam ſi poteſt è medio tollat,</hi> let euerie pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man reſiſt him, and if he can, take away his life. For the Tyrant exercent: hauing deſcribed him to be a Prince, that doth wilfully diſſolue all, or the chiefeſt compacts of the commonwealth, he concludeth againſt him, <hi>Hunc tollant, vel Pacifice vel cum Bello, qui ea poteſtate donati ſunt, vt rgeni Ephori vel omnium ordinum conventus publicus:</hi> The Peeres of the kingdome or the publique aſſembly of ſtates, ought to deſtroy him, either by peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able practiſes, or open warre. <hi>haec ille.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1588. <hi>Hermanus Renecherus</hi> publiſhed obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon the firſt <hi>Pſalme,</hi> wherein he inveſteth the <hi>Preſbiterie</hi> with all the <hi>Popes</hi> prerogatiues. Concerning the <hi>Preſbiterian power</hi> ouer kings. This is his notable an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notation:<note place="margin">pag. 72.</note> God (ſaith he) hath ordained the Ciuill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate for the good of the eccleſiaſticall order, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eccleſiaſtical ſtate is the higheſt throne of Gods earthly kingdome, the ſupreame ſeate of all excellencie, and the chiefeſt court wherin God himſelfe is preſident, to diſtribute eternall gifts to his ſervants. Whereas the politicall Empire is but as it were an inferiour bench, wherein iuſtice is adminiſtred according to the preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the eccleſiaſticall ſoueraigntie: Thus fatre <hi>Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Rollocke,</hi> a man otherwiſe verie learned, is caried with the current of this error, and borrowed his aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of M. <hi>Fenner,</hi> whoſe words he expoundeth by way of <hi>paraphraſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Daniel. c. 5. p. 150.</note> in his commentaries on <hi>Daniel</hi> printed at <hi>Edingburge,</hi> 1591. Though the chiefe lawfull Magiſtrate
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14168:35"/>
(ſaith <hi>M. Rollocke</hi>) doe many things vniuſtly and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly, he may not raſhly be violated, by them eſpecially which haue not authoritie: but the Nobles or the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like aſſemblie of ſtates, muſt reduce him to his dutie, by reproofe and all other lawfull meanes, 1. Sam. 14.46. If he doe ſtill perſiſt in open and deſperate tyrannie, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſſoluing all or the chiefeſt compacts of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, priuate men muſt not yet medle with him, onely the Peeres, or the publike aſſemblie of all ſtates to whom that charge belongeth, muſt prouide that the Church and Commonwealth come not to deſolation: though it cannot otherwiſe be done, then by the death and deſtruction of the tyrant. Better it is that an euill king be deſtroyed, then the Church and ſtate together ruined. Thus farre <hi>Rollocke.</hi> For proofe he referreth his reader firſt to the 1. Sam. 14.46. <hi>viz. Then Saul came vp from the Philiſtims, and the Philiſtims went to their own place: ergo</hi> Kings that are wicked may be reduced to their dutie by the Peeres, or aſſemblie of ſtates according to the rules of the newe <hi>Puritan logique.</hi> Secondly, for the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and deſtroying of kings, he referreth his readers to the 2. <hi>regum</hi> c. 11. v. 4.5.6.7. which place I thinke he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vouchſafed to looke vpon, but ſet it downe as he found it quoted in <hi>Fenners</hi> diuinitie, from whom he hath taken all the reſt.</p>
            <p>I will make an end with <hi>William Bucanus,</hi> whoſe booke was publiſhed at the requeſt, and with the approbation of <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Goulartius,</hi> maine pillars of the Church of <hi>Geneva.</hi> 1602.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> They (ſaith <hi>Bucanus</hi>) which haue any part of office in the publike adminiſtration of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, as the Ouerſeers, Senators, Conſuls, Peeres,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14168:36"/>
or Tribunes, may reſtraine the inſolencie of euill kings. Thus farre he.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Puritan-dangerous</hi> error is directly repugnant to the Law, the Goſpel, the precepts of the Apoſtles, the practiſe of Martyrs, and the doctrine of the Fathers, Councels, and other claſſicall Writers, as I haue proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the ſixe former Chapters: and will more directly ſhew (by the grace of God) in my other booke: wherein the holy texts of Scripture, which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> doe damnably abuſe againſt the Eccleſiaſticall and Civill authoritie of Kings, ſhall be anſwered by the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Proteſtants: whoſe labour God vſed to reforme his Church ſince the yeare of our Lord, 1517. and by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers and orthodoxall Writers in euery age of the Church. This <hi>Puritan-poſition,</hi> which authoriſeth Nobles and aſſemblies of States againſt wicked kings, is the very aſſertion of the moſt ſeditious Ieſuits, that haue liued in our age, as I will demonſtrate by two or three: <hi>Iohannes Mariana,</hi> whoſe booke ſeemeth to be written in defence of <hi>Clement</hi> the fryer, who ſtabbed <hi>Henrie</hi> the 3. king of France. The faults and licentiouſnes of kings (ſaith <hi>Mariana</hi>) whether they raigne by conſent of the people,<note place="margin">de regis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. 1. c. 6.</note> or right of inheritance, are to be borne and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, ſo long as the laws of ſhamefaſtnes and honeſtie, whereto all men be bound, are not violated: for Princes ſhould not raſhly be diſturbed, leaſt the commonwealth fall into greater miſerie and calamitie. But if the Prince make hauock of the commonwealth, and expoſe the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate fortunes of his ſubiects for a pray to other men, if he deſpiſe law, &amp; contemne religion, this courſe muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt him. Let him be admoniſhed and recalled to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14168:36"/>
his dutie: if he repent, ſatisfie the Wealepublike, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his faults, there ought (as I thinke) to be no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceeding againſt him. But if there be no hope of his amendment, the commonwealth may take away his kingdome. And becauſe that cannot be done (in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihoode) without warre, they may leuie power, brandiſh their blades againſt their king, and exact money of the people, for the maintenance of their warre: for when there is no other helpe, the Peeres of the common wealth, hauing proclaimed their king a publike enemy, may take away his life. Thus farre <hi>Mariana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Stateſmen of the Kingdome (ſaith <hi>Franciſcus Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vardentius</hi>) haue a ſoueraigne power ouer their Kings:<note place="margin">In Heſter. c. 1. pag. 88.</note> for Kings are not abſolutely eſtabliſhed, but ſtand bound to obſerue lawes, conditions, and compacts, to their ſubiects: the which, if they violate, they are no lawfull Kings, but theeues and tyrants, puniſhable by the ſtates. Thus farre <hi>Feuardentius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inferiour Magiſtrates (ſaith <hi>Iohannes Baptiſta Ficklerus</hi>) are the defenders and protectours of the lawes and rightes of the ſtate,<note place="margin">de iure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt. fol. 18.</note> and haue authoritie (if need require) to correct and puniſh the ſupreame King. So farre <hi>Fick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Engliſh fugitiue, which was the author of the booke <hi>de iuſta abdicatione Henrici Tertij,</hi> affirmeth, That all the Maieſtie of the kingdome, is in the aſſembly of Stateſmen, to whom it belongeth to make couenants with God, to diſpoſe of the affaires of the kingdome, to appoint matters pertaining to warre and peace,<note place="margin">l b 3. cap 8.</note> to bridle the kingly power, and to ſettle all things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to publique gouernment. So farre he.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14168:37"/>
               <note place="margin">part. 1 c. 4. pag 72.</note>And the moſt ſeditious <hi>Doleman</hi> ſaith, that all humane lawe and order naturall, Nationall, and poſitiue, doth teach, that the commonwealth, which gaue Kings their authoritie for the common good, may reſtraine or take the ſame from them if they abuſe it to the common ill: ſo farre <hi>Doleman,</hi> and of this opinion are many other as may appeare by D. <hi>Morton</hi> by whom they are diſcouered and refuted.</p>
            <p>How farre this gangrene will extend, I knowe not. The kings of Chriſtendome are daily crucified, (as Chriſt their Lord was) betweene two theeues; I meane the <hi>Papist</hi> and <hi>Puritan,</hi> which haue prepared this dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poyſon for Princes, whom they in their owne irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and traiterous hearts, ſhall condemne for tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. I hope neither Peeres nor people will be ſo fond to beleeue them, or wicked to followe them, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the reformation of religion, and defend the ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtian ſtates. If inferiour officers, or the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like aſſembly of all States, will claime this power, it ſtandeth them vpon, (as they wil avoid euerlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation) not to deriue a title from Rome, Lacedemon, or Athens, (as <hi>Calvin</hi> doth, whom the reſt followe) but from the hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> and to plead their intereſt from the law or the goſpell.<note place="margin">Auguſt. in queſt. mixt.</note> 
               <hi>Si mandatum non eſt praeſumptio est, &amp; ad paenam proficiet, non ad praemium: quia ad contumeliam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet conditoris, vt contempto Domino colantur ſervi, &amp; ſpreto Imperatore, adorentur Comites.</hi> If their oppoſition againſt Kings be not commanded of God, it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption againſt God: for it is a contumely againſt God the creator of all ſtates, to deſpiſe Lords and honour ſeruants, to contemne the ſoueraigne Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14168:37"/>
and to reuerence the Peeres of the Empire. So farre <hi>Auguſtine. My ſonne</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) feare God and the King, and meddle not with the ſeditious:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 24.21.</note> 
               <hi>for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ſhall come ſodainly, and who knoweth the end of them?</hi> The concluſion of all is, That Kings haue ſupreame and abſolute authoritie vnder God on earth, not becauſe all things are ſubiect to their pleaſure, which were plaine tyrannie, not Chriſtian ſoueraigntie: but becauſe all perſons, within their dominions, ſtand bound in lawe, allegiance, and conſcience, to obey their pleaſure, or to abide their puniſhment. And Kings themſelues, are no way ſubiect to the controwle, cenſure, or puniſhment, of any earthly man, but reſerued by ſpeciall prerogatiue to the moſt fearefull and righteous iudgement of God, with whome there is no reſpect of perſons. He whoſe ſeruants they are, <hi>will beate them with a rod of iron, and breake them in peeces like a potters veſſell,</hi> if they abuſe that great, and ſoueraigne power, (which God hath endued them withall,) to ſupport error, to ſuppreſſe truth, and to oppreſſe the innocent. God, of his great mercie, graunt vs the ſpirit of truth, to direct vs in all loyaltie, that we beeing not ſeduced by theſe ſeditious Sectaries, may growe in grace, ſtand faſt in obedience, embrace loue, follow peace, and encreaſe more and more in the knowledge of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. To whom be all praiſe, power, and dominion now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
